<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The ordering of bees: or, The true history of managing them from time to time, with their hony and waxe, shewing their nature and breed As also what trees, plants, and hearbs are good for them, and namely what are hurtfull: together with the extraordinary profit arising from them. Set forth in a dialogue, resolving all doubts whatsoever. By the late unparalell'd experience of Iohn Levett, Gent.</title>
            <author>Levett, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1634</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 157 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 46 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05403</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15555</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108514</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844172</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844172</idno>
            <idno type="VID">159996</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05403)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 159996)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 806:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The ordering of bees: or, The true history of managing them from time to time, with their hony and waxe, shewing their nature and breed As also what trees, plants, and hearbs are good for them, and namely what are hurtfull: together with the extraordinary profit arising from them. Set forth in a dialogue, resolving all doubts whatsoever. By the late unparalell'd experience of Iohn Levett, Gent.</title>
                  <author>Levett, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 71, [1] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Harper, for Iohn Harison,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1634.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes index.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bee culture --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:159996:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <lg>
                     <l>He who by Bees doth ever thinke to thrive,</l>
                     <l>Muſt order them, and neatly trim his Hive.</l>
                  </lg>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:159996:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The ordering of Bees:</hi> OR, THE TRVE HISTORY OF MANAGING THEM From time to time, with their hony and waxe, ſhewing their nature and Breed.</p>
            <p>As alſo what Trees, Plants, and Hearbs are good for them, and namely what are hurtfull: toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the extraordinary profit ariſing from them.</p>
            <p>Set forth in a Dialogue, reſolving all doubts whatſoever.</p>
            <p>By the late unparell'd experience <hi>of IOHN LEVETT,</hi> Gent.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>I H</head>
               <q>DVM SPERO FERO</q>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device of John Harrison (?)</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Thomas Harper,</hi> for <hi>John Hariſon,</hi> 1634.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:159996:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:159996:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE VERTVOVS gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman M<hi rend="sup">rs.</hi> 
               <hi>Dorothy Kemp,</hi> wife to the Right Worſhipfull M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Robert Kemp,</hi> Eſquire, one of his Maieſties Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of Peace in the County of <hi>Northfolk.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſt vertuous and kinde, J here preſent unto your hands and view, this Treatiſe not great, of a ſubiect in ſeeming ſmall, indeed full of greatneſſe and glory. For howſoever the body of this little creature, while ſhe is under ſayle on her airy voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, can ſcarce be apprehended of ſenſe; yet the admirable power and manifold wiſdome of the Creator, manifeſted in this his working work, cannot bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended by reaſon, no not by the indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious
<pb facs="tcp:159996:3"/>inquiſitors into her buſie induſtry. This therefore hath in many ages buſied many of the moſt learned of Natures Secretaries, to obſerve the nature, work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, policy, thrift, and exquiſite perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this little Flie, in all affayres of war or peace, at home or abroad: and yet have they all beene rather brought to height of admiration, than made fit for full expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the wiſdome which (ſurpaſsing their owne wiſdome) they have found in the Bee. Among others, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of this Booke, Father to my ſelfe and it, was a ſcholler of this ſchoole, and hat thus written of their orders and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering; which he not living to publiſh, J have preſumed to ſet forth under your Name, as the heire of that love and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which he bare to the common good, and your ſelfe; whom in regard of birth, qualities, and fortunes, as gentle, friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb facs="tcp:159996:3"/>and the most worthy wife of a moſt worthy husband, he alwayes highly eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. J hope therefore, that (to be ſilent of my ſelfe) either of your own generous diſpoſition, or your love to the deceaſed Author, or your charity to this poſthume Orphling, you will moſt heartily accept what I moſt heartily dedicate, together with my ſelfe, unto you.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips in all duty, IOHN LEVETT.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:159996:4"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:159996:4"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ecauſe it is the moſt uſuall manner (friendly Reader) of thoſe that pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh any thing in writing, to beſtow an Epiſtle upon the courteous and well affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Reader, I reſolved alſo to follow the ſame order: But I ſtood long in doubt, whether I ſhould do it by way of Apology, for ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chargeing the world with more books, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of that ſeemeth overfull; for writing of ſo meane a ſubject, when all mens minds conceit great matters: or for that my ſelfe, being one of the leaſt, ſhould preſume to thruſt in my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion among ſo many rare, and excellent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions found out by the curious wits of theſe dayes: or elſe following the moſt ordinary and old faſhion, when all men enquire after new, I ſhould fall to commendation of the matter I write of, and the profit and commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity that may grow by the well-ordering of the ſame. Yet at the laſt I determined to ſay ſomething concerning them all.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:159996:5"/>they account a part thereof; whom our Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh writers following, have not a little erred. And this is the cauſe that concerning the order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and keeping of Bees, little is found amongſt them (ſome precepts of Mr. <hi>Southerns</hi> only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted) worthy remembrance.</p>
            <p>And although that for the breeding, indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, art, and government of Bees, they have written many curious and good obſervations of the Ancients, which are worthy the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, eſpecially of ſuch as keep Bees; againe, I was not much diſwaded from my intention, becauſe the greateſt uſe of this book will be for the unlearned and Country people, eſpecially good women, who commonly in this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try take moſt care and regard of this kinde of commodity, (although much the worſe for the poore Bees) becauſe ſometimes they want help, ſometimes diligence, but moſt times know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge how to uſe them well. And this princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally moved me to undertake this work, which I have performed without Art or Eloquence, and after a different method or order from all thoſe which have formerly written of Bees, having ſet down every thing that I ſuppoſed worthy obſervatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And notwithſtanding ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb facs="tcp:159996:5"/>of them at the firſt ſight may peradventure ſeeme to bee of little worth, or elſe needleſſe, for being commonly known to moſt that keep Bees: Yet I would intreat your patience in reading of thoſe alſo, and I ſuppoſe that my purpoſe being to teach, I was unwilling to omit any thing (were it never ſo little) worthy the noting. Moreover, have I written any thing contrary to the common received opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, or different from your conceit; bee not over haſty to cenſure it, but obſerve and then try before you give iudgement. And thus much by way of Apology. Laſt of all, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with the excellency of hony and wax, let this only ſuffice, that they are numbred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the notable and chiefe commodities of ſome Kingdomes, and the very Land of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe it ſelfe, to give the Iſraelites a better liking unto it, was called the Land that flowed, or to uſe our Engliſh phraſe, abounded with Milk and Hony, which were eſteemed at that time, amongſt the principall earthly commodities that were to bee expected from the bleſſing of God. And as for the profit of this booke, I referre it to the ſucceſſe that it ſhall pleaſe God to give in the uſe of it.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>And ſo Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="memorial">
            <pb facs="tcp:159996:6"/>
            <head>TO THE MEMORIE OF THE THRICE WORTHY Gentleman, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. IOHN LEVETT deceaſed: and to the eternity of his <hi>well-taken-labour in this moſt</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and profitable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation and Hiſtory of BEES.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are two immortall enemies, which, like Butchers dogges (whoſe mouthes are ever bloudy) do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually beſiege and aſſault everie good labour, and that is, Curioſitie and Envie; the firſt ſtriving to finde out knots in Ruſhes or Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles beyond mans capacitie: the other devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and gnawing upon all vertuous Actions, till, with the poyſon of her corrupt Nature, ſhe have brought all wholſome Intents within the compaſſe of ſcandall; with theſe two enemies, if this excellent and well-taken-labour chance not to encounter, it may paſſe into the world with infinite applauſe, and well-liking of all men, being a worke ſo exact and compendiouſly done. So plaine and eaſie for the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt
<pb facs="tcp:159996:6"/>underſtanding, yet with all ſo ſuccinct, deepe, and elaborate, that as a Flie may eaſily wade it, ſo an Elephant may with difficultie ſwimme in it, not that there are unreſolved <hi>Enigmas</hi> or things fetcht beyond the clouds to adorne it, but becauſe the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments being new, approved, and allyed both to truth and Reaſon, the collections ſo manifeſt, and not to be controlled, the corrections and reconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the errours of others former publiſhings, ſo modeſtly handled, cleared, and adorned, and the whole worke ſo purged from all gloſſe or flouriſh of ayrie words, from the folly of amazing Inventions, and from the intricate windings, turnings, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnings of a wilde braine, which many times carries the Reader into a new world farre beyond all his acquaintance; That here every good man and good Minde ſhall finde as much as he can expect, and yet no more then is ſufficient. For mine owne part, I have had a ſingular affection, and an earneſt deſire in the purſuit of this knowledge, and was once a great Maſter of theſe creatures; neither have I ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to beſtow my pen in the advancement of the Art and knowledge of the Bee; yet not with that felicitie and happineſſe which this Gentleman hath attained unto, to whom I cannot chuſe but allow all
<pb facs="tcp:159996:7"/>poſsible praiſe and eſtimation; confeſsing ingeniouſly that I have not read or ſeene any worke of this Nature more exact and compleat then this is. And howſoever others have, or may adde more words, more quaint deviſes, and more amazing <hi>Meanders,</hi> yet the ſubstance of the Art, and the excellent things which are meet to inrich and adorne every good mans knowledge, cannot be better or more fully diſcuſſed: for here you ſhall know what the Bee is, his breeding and government, how to order him, houſe him, and maintaine him, how to remove him, purge him from injuries, and to preſerue his health, of ſwarming, driving, hoyſting, and deſtroying things ſuperfluous. And laſtly of their profits, and how thoſe profits are to be diſpoſed, and what ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodations are neceſſarie for the ſupport and encreaſe of ſo uſefull and delicate a commonwealth. And he that in this Art will looke beyond this, let him looke beyond the Moone, I will neither lend him mine eyes nor my commendations.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Admirer GERVASE MARKHAM.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem" subtype="to_the__reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:159996:7"/>
            <head>I. S. ad lectorem.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>FOr profit, pleasure, policy, and fame,</l>
               <l>High pregnant wits themſelves have loſt to finde,</l>
               <l>But couched here lo under <hi>Levetts</hi> name,</l>
               <l>These vertues grave, flow from his godly minde:</l>
               <l>Athenians looke for news of other kinde,</l>
               <l>Fables not truth, their fanſies for to feed,</l>
               <l>Sure vertue is news, who is to her inclinde,</l>
               <l>Vertue is gone <hi>Maecenas</hi> being dead.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>From Court and City to the Country fled,</l>
               <l>Obſcure she lives amongſt her rurall friends,</l>
               <l>Thence by her beames are little Bees diſcried,</l>
               <l>Their wit, their work, their policy and kindes:</l>
               <l>But pore not much upon this regall race,</l>
               <l>Lest ere you know, they ſting you on the face.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Idem.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Non quantum ſed quale, Iovis primordia parva,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rebus in exiguis grandia ſaepe latent.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:159996:8"/>
            <head>S. Purcas.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>VNskild am I to uſher forth thy Book,</l>
               <l>Or blaze thy ſelfe with termes of commendation,</l>
               <l>(Nor buſie Bees ſuch idle court' ſies brook,</l>
               <l>Nor can I rules queint affected faſhion.)</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thy ſelfe, thy ſelfe enough, enough thy Booke,</l>
               <l>Thy Book commends, and I, my <hi>Levett,</hi> leave it,</l>
               <l>Here in ſmall Bees, Gods greatneſſe firſt I looke,</l>
               <l>And then thy ſelfe though dead to live yet.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Induſtrious Fly, fly forth, and ſound him farre,</l>
               <l>Which here ſounds thee, thy nature, art, thrift, keeping,</l>
               <l>Much can he prayſe thy peace, and much thy warre,</l>
               <l>Modell of policy, a ſweet good ſeeking:</l>
               <l>And in thoſe lazy Drones thy ſting fix ſure,</l>
               <l>Which nor their own, nor others paynes can dure.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:159996:8"/>
            <head>Idem ad I. L. Editorem hujus libelli.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>VVEll haſt thou ſhewed the world thy fathers worth,</l>
               <l>(As by the foot is known in Symetry</l>
               <l>The body whole) when thou this Book ſett'ſt forth,</l>
               <l>Iuſt witneſſe of his wit and induſtry.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And though he never ſipp'd at <hi>Hipocrene,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor clymb'd <hi>Parnaſſus</hi> top, he well deviſed</l>
               <l>Of Mathematicks, (which no Academe</l>
               <l>Him taught) but ſtudious paines, and time high priſed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Of policy of States, of peace, of warre,</l>
               <l>Of natures art, plants, planting, lands to meaſure,</l>
               <l>Of Hiſtories, times, places, neere and farre</l>
               <l>Off; oh, but death hath rob'd us of this treaſure:</l>
               <l>Earth hath his earth, heaven his heavenly part, his name</l>
               <l>Thou here intomb'ſt while Bees there be in fame.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:159996:9"/>
            <head>Nos quoque noſtra A. Cook.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>Let Bees be prayſed by that Latian Bard</l>
               <l>That ſweetly ſang their occupation,</l>
               <l>(Enriching with his ſong, his ſong rich nation,</l>
               <l>Himſelfe with never dying fames reward.)</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>While thee we prayſe with hearty loves regard,</l>
               <l>That haſt ſet forth this ſweet Flyes operation,</l>
               <l>With <hi>Maro's</hi> skill, though in another faſhion,</l>
               <l>To thee thy Country men like fame anward.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Oh had thy Countrymen enioyd thee ſtill,</l>
               <l>How many choiſe fruits had they reapt by thee,</l>
               <l>Which now death envies to poſterity,</l>
               <l>What art-ſurpaſsing drops did heaven diſtill</l>
               <l>Into that graden where this plant did grow,</l>
               <l>And thouſands more which natures hand did ſtow?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The winged Citizens of mount <hi>Hymete</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(Forſaking once their flowry manſion)</l>
               <l>Flew down to <hi>Athens</hi> laden with ſweet meat</l>
               <l>For infant <hi>Plato's</hi> mouth to feed upon.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There did they turn his cradle to a hive,</l>
               <l>And gently buzzing, harmleſſe buſſes gave him,</l>
               <l>Thereby preſaging that his name ſhould live,</l>
               <l>And that his wiſdome from to dy ſhould ſave him.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I ſaw a ſwarm deſcended of that ſtock,</l>
               <l>Fly to our Authors tomb, from whence proceeds</l>
               <l>This poſthume birth conceiv'd of heavenly ſeed,</l>
               <l>I heard the humming of that airy flock,</l>
               <l>Mourning his death; then ſwearing on this book,</l>
               <l>His fame as they ſhould dure, their flight they took.</l>
            </lg>
            <bibl>
               <hi>L. M. utcunque P.</hi>
            </bibl>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:159996:9"/>
            <head>A Table of the principall heads con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in this Booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>REmoving of Bees <hi>page.</hi> 1</item>
               <item>Coating of Bees <hi>page.</hi> 9</item>
               <item>Ordering of Bees in the Spring <hi>page.</hi> 14</item>
               <item>Chuſing of Hives <hi>page.</hi> 16</item>
               <item>Trimming of Hives <hi>page.</hi> 19</item>
               <item>Swarming of Bees <hi>page.</hi> 21</item>
               <item>Hoyſting of Bees <hi>page.</hi> 32</item>
               <item>Killing of Drones <hi>page.</hi> 34</item>
               <item>To know if Bees will live <hi>page.</hi> 37</item>
               <item>Of driving of Bees <hi>page.</hi> 39</item>
               <item>The ordering of Honey <hi>page.</hi> 49</item>
               <item>The ordering of waxe <hi>page.</hi> 51</item>
               <item>Trees and Plants. good for Bees <hi>page.</hi> 52</item>
               <item>The nature of Bees <hi>page.</hi> 58</item>
               <item>The breeding of Bees <hi>page.</hi> 61</item>
               <item>Of the maſter Bee <hi>page.</hi> 65</item>
               <item>The government of Bees. <hi>page.</hi> 69</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="index">
            <pb facs="tcp:159996:10"/>
            <head>An Alphabeticall Table of all the things contained in this Booke.</head>
            <list>
               <head>A</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>A</hi> Bricots good for Bees <hi>page 53</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ayre how hurtfull <hi>page 13</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Angelica good for Bees <hi>page 57</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ants hurtfull to Bees <hi>page 8</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Apple trees good for Bees <hi>page 53</hi>
               </item>
               <item>when to plant them <hi>page 54</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Avens good for Bees <hi>page 57</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Author his way of Coating of Hives. <hi>page 10</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>B</head>
               <item>Balme good for Bees <hi>page 57</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Baſons not to be rung <hi>page 23</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Barley good for Bees <hi>page 21</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Bearefoot good for Bees <hi>page 55</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Beanes good for Bees <hi>page 55</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Bees are lovers of quietneſſe <hi>page 58</hi>
               </item>
               <item>how to place them <hi>6.</hi> of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Bee <hi>31.32.64.67.</hi> how long Bees will ſwarme <hi>36.</hi> to know if Bees will live <hi>37.</hi> the beſt ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſous for Bees <hi>38.39.</hi> if Bees be to be killed <hi>41.</hi> how long Bees will live <hi>46.</hi> guelding of Bees, <hi>Ibid,</hi> the nature of Bees <hi>58.</hi> the breding of Bees <hi>61.</hi> the governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Bees <hi>page 69</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Black-berry buſh good for Bees <hi>page 57</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Box tree hurtfull to Bees <hi>page 57</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Buck-Hyſſope good for Bees <hi>page 57</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Burrage good for Bees <hi>page 55</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>C</head>
               <item>Cabbages good for Bees <hi>page 55</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Cherry trees good for Bees <hi>page 53</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Claver good for Bees <hi>page 57</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Coating of hives <hi>9.10.</hi> when to Coate <hi>page 29</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Cow dung good for Bees <hi>page 15</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Combes how to order <hi>page 51</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Cucumbers hurtfull to Bees <hi>page 57</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>D</head>
               <item>Driving of Hives how, when, and the uſe <hi>39.41.42.47.</hi> the benefits <hi>43.</hi> choyce of ſtockes to drive, <hi>44.</hi> avoyding inconveniences in driving. <hi>page 49</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Droanes whether to be killed, how and when <hi>43.</hi> their iniurie <hi>page 41</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dung hurtfull to trees <hi>page 54</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>E</head>
               <item>Elme hurtfull to Bees <hi>page 57</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>F</head>
               <item>Feeding of Bees <hi>page 14</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>G</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Googe</hi> confuted <hi>page 47</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:159996:10"/>
               <item>Guelding of Bees <hi>page 47</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>H</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hils</hi> opinion for killing of Droanes <hi>page 35</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Hives how to be placed <hi>6.8.</hi> the dawbing of Hives, <hi>ibid.</hi> hurts in ſetting Hives too cloſe, <hi>7.</hi> the choyce <hi>16.17.18.</hi> Hives muſt not be too broad <hi>18.</hi> the trim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Hives <hi>19.</hi> anoynting <hi>20.</hi> what Hives have moſt ſtore of Honey <hi>page 45</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Honey when moſt plentifull <hi>26.</hi> how to order it <hi>page 49</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Hoyſting of Bees <hi>page 33.34</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>I</head>
               <item>Iramboys good for Bees <hi>page 55</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>L</head>
               <item>Lavender good for Bees <hi>page 57</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Liſimachus good for Bees <hi>page 57</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>M</head>
               <item>Mallowes good for Bees <hi>page 57</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mault good for Bees <hi>page 20</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mayweed hurtfull for Bees <hi>page 57</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mellilot good for Bees <hi>page 57</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mice enemies to Bees <hi>page 68</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Moathes enemies to Bees. <hi>page 44</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>O</head>
               <item>Olibanum good for Bees. <hi>page 15</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>P</head>
               <item>Pallatilla good for Bees <hi>page 55</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Peach trees good for Bees <hi>page 53</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Peaſe good for Bees <hi>page 20</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Plants good and hurtfull for Bees <hi>page 52</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Plinie</hi> of the nature of Bees <hi>page 59</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Plumb trees good for Bees <hi>page 53</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ponds how hurtfull <hi>page 8</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Primroſe good for Bees <hi>page 56</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>R</head>
               <item>Rapes good for Bees <hi>page 55</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Raſpis good for Bees <hi>page 55</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Removing of Bees, <hi>4.12.</hi> obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in removing, <hi>ibid.</hi> the time of the yeare, <hi>ibid.</hi> how they ſhould ſtand <hi>page 5</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Rivers how hurtfull <hi>page 8</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Roſemary good for Bees <hi>page 54</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>S</head>
               <item>Sage good for Bees <hi>page 57</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sallow good for Bees <hi>page 56</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sarazanica good for Bees <hi>page 57</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Snayles enemies to Bees <hi>page 6</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Solidago good for Bees <hi>Southernes</hi> way of Coating of Hyves <hi>page 10</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Spat of Bees. <hi>page 62</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Spiders enemies to Bees <hi>page 44</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Spurge hurtfull to Bees <hi>page 57</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Stecados good for Bees <hi>page 57</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sticking of Hives <hi>page 19</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Swarmes when to be attended, <hi>page 21</hi>
               </item>
               <item>how ordered <hi>22.</hi> that but one ſwarme riſe at one time <hi>24.</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther many ſwarmes from one Hyve <hi>25.</hi> in what ſeaſon they ſwarme moſt, <hi>ibid.</hi> putting di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ſwarmes in one Hive, and how, <hi>27.</hi> when Bees will ſwarme <hi>30.</hi> to hinder Bees from ſwarm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>32.33.</hi> how long ſwarmes may riſe without danger <hi>36.</hi> what ſwarmes to ſave. <hi>page 1</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>Thime good for Bees <hi>page 57</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:159996:11"/>
               <item>Toades hurtfull to Bees. <hi>page 8</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Trees good and hurtfull for Bees <hi>page 52</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Trimming of Hives <hi>page 19</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Turneps good for <hi>Bees page 55</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>V</head>
               <item>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iolets good for Bees <hi>page 56</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Virgil</hi> on the Maſter Bee <hi>page 66</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>W</head>
               <item>Waxe how to order <hi>page 51</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Weſterne honey not good <hi>page 49</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Wicker Hives <hi>page 18</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Winde and weather how to defend Bees from them <hi>page 9</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Woade hurtfull to Bees <hi>page 57</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Wormes hurtfull to Bees <hi>page 8.44</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Wormewood hurtfull to Bees <hi>page 57</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Y</head>
               <item>Yewe tree hurtfull to Bees. <hi>page 57</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:159996:11"/>
            <head>A DIALOGVE CONCERNING THE ORDERING OF <hi>BEES.</hi>
            </head>
            <stage>Tortona. Petralba.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ortona.</speaker>
               <p>Well met good neighbour <hi>Petralba,</hi> but whether away ſo faſt man, thus early in the morning? I ſuppoſe your buſineſſe is impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, you make ſo much haſte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba,</speaker>
               <p>O I cry you mercy Sir, I ſaw you not before you ſpake; in good ſooth I was even comming to you, my friend and kinſman that was, <hi>Philippo Ambroſia,</hi> having (as you know) made me his Executor, amongſt ſome other things, hath left me ſome eight or tenne Hyves of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:159996:12"/>Bees, which at the firſt I made ſmall account of, but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter my buſineſſe of greater regard was over, I beganne to looke over his Bookes, amongſt which I found theſe diſcourſes or Pamphlets concerning the ordering of Bees: whereupon I began not onely to conſider the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit reported to ariſe and come of them, but alſo to take eſpeciall delight, as well in their order and government, reſembling the forme (if they report the truth) of a moſt exquiſite and well governed Common-wealth, as alſo admired their notable arte and induſtry, in framing of their combes, gathering of their honey, and other la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and great travailes to maintaine and preſerve themſelues and their Brood.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>Good neighbour <hi>Petralba,</hi> there is no man more welcome unto mee then your ſelfe, and I am very glad that any cauſe hath made you to take pleaſure and delight in Bees, becauſe my ſelfe as you know, doe alſo the ſame. For by this meanes I ſhall have a companion to converſe withall: for according to the old Proverbe, <hi>ſimile ſimili gaudet,</hi> and that may-communicate with me in the ſame pleaſures, and ſo make them the more delightſome unto mee, which for want of conference with ſuch as take pleaſure in the ſame, ſeeme often wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſome and irkeſome unto me. And to talke of Bees to thoſe that love them not, is like muſicke out of tune, or a pleaſant tale told to the ſorrowfull. But wherefore doe you bring your Bookes with you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>Marry Sir, although my Bookes have ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up in me ſome affection towards Bees (as before I ſaid) and have ſome what informed me of the manner how to uſe them, at the leaſt in my conceit, yet know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your great practice and long experience amongſt Bees, with the plentifull increaſe, and profit that I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:159996:12"/>you make of them (by that little that I have read of the profit of Bees) I made bold to conferre with you firſt, before I put in practice any of thoſe preceps that are taught in theſe my bookes, and for that cauſe I have not ſtirred nor meddled with them as yet, untill I might perceive how your opinion agreed with their writings, or diſſented from the ſame, and this was the cauſe that I brought my bookes with me. Againe, my purpoſe is ſhortly to remove them to mine owne houſe, if you thinke the time fit and convenient for the ſame.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>Concerning the time fit for their remove, I will tell you my opinion hereafter, but firſt let me know whoſe works thoſe bookes are that you have brought with you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>The one is that which we commonly call <hi>Googe</hi> his husbandry, who amongſt many other pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of husbandry concludeth his worke with a Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of the ordering of Bees: the other is a Pamphlet ſet forth by one Maſter <hi>Southerne;</hi> to the ſame purpoſe I have alſo ſeene a booke called the Country Farme, lately ſet forth, wherein alſo there is ſomewhat ſaid concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this matter, I make no doubt but you have ſeene them all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>Yea verily I doe know them well: the firſt of them is principally a ſhort collection, gathered out of the works of ſundry learned men that have long ſince written of Bees: as <hi>Ariſtotle, Virgil, Varro, Pliny, Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, Collumella, Didmus, Dionyſius, Thaſeus,</hi> and others: rather then any great knowledge or experience that himſelfe ſeemeth to have had in the ordering of Bees. But the other is onely certaine practiſes and experiments gathered by his owne obſervations, by long keeping of Bees as himſelfe confeſſeth. Both which workes no
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:159996:13"/>doubt are worthy of commendations, and have profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted many, yet neither the one with his authorities, nor the other with his experiments doe ſo fully intreate of them, but that much more may be added, and many things alſo are alleadged by them, which for mine owne part I cannot approve, but do hold them altogether im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent or dangerous.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>Surely my ſelfe imagined no leſſe, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I am not able to diſtinguiſh the good from the counterfeit, I was deſirous to conferre with you (as I ſaid) before I meddied with them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>You muſt underſtand before that you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move them, it ſhall not bee amiſſe for you to obſerve three things. Firſt, the fitteſt time for their remove and the manner how to doe it. Secondly, a place convenient and good for them to ſtand in: and thirdly, the order and manner how to place and ſet them. Now concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the time of their remove, I hold it not much mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall ſo it be carefully, gently, and quietly done, with as little ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>irring them as may be; yet doe I thinke the beſt time to be betweene the moneths of <hi>Ianuary</hi> and <hi>May,</hi> having eſpeciall care to keepe them as much from the ayre and cold as is poſſible, which will doe them much hurt at that time of the yeere. And the worſt time of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move I hold to be betweene the beginning of <hi>May</hi> and <hi>November,</hi> for at that time of the yeere they are either full of Bees, or elſe heauy with honey, and by that means are apt to take hurt by much troubling the Bees, or ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and breaking the Combes, and conſequently of ſpilling and ſpoyling their honey. But for Swarmes the beſt time to remove them, is as ſoone as may be after they are ſwarmed. And concerning the fitteſt place to ſet them in you are well informed in your bookes, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:159996:13"/>in ſome Garden or Orchard or other ſeverall place, free from cattell or much reſort, if it may be, for they are great lovers of quietneſſe, and hate the contrary: againe, it were good they had the South and Weſt Sunne open unto them, but if they be defended from the Eaſt and North, it is much the better, be it either by pale, hedge, trees, houſing, or ſuch like. You muſt alſo obſerve that a hill or mountainous place is not good for them, becauſe they will be the more ſubiect to ſtormes and wind, which is very hurtfull and perillous for them, and doth exceedingly hinder them in their labour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>Maſter <hi>Googe</hi> ſaith, that the place of their ſtanding would neither be to hot nor to cold, but as tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate as may be, ſo as they be neither offended with the cold of Winter, nor the heate of Summer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>In more hotter regions, as in <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> I am of their mind which ſo affirme, yet could I never perceive that Bees were offended with the heate of any place that ever I could ſee in this Country: pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided that their Hives be well coated (as I will after ſhew) to defend them from the heate of Summer and the extremity of cold in Winter, for otherwiſe the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame heate of the Sunne in the Summer may melt their Combes, and cauſe their honey to runne out, as many times I have ſeene amongſt my neighbours Bees, where proviſion hath not beene made to prevent it. And againe the extreame froſts in Winter will ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nume them, as they being pinched therewith, will fall out of their Combes and preſently dye; and all for lacke of warme keeping of them: both which extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities may bee prevented by one remedy namely, by the coating of their Hives, as after ſhall bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:159996:14"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>Well Sir, now let me have your opinion concerning the manner of placing or ſetting of them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>Touching the manner of placing of them, Maſter <hi>Southerne</hi> hath written very well, and therefore I will diſcent from him very little, becauſe I hold his Iudgement the beſt therein of any that I have read. And firſt to begin with all, I would have every Hive placed upon a ſeverall plancke board or ſtone, within two foote of the ground at the moſt, for ſo the winds will have the leſſe power over them at the entrance into the Hive. And the plancke, board, or ſtone whereupon the Hive ſtandeth, muſt be ſome three or foure Inches at the leaſt broader then the Hive on the South part, where the hole or mouth of the Hive muſt be, for ſo the Bees ſhall have roome to light upon it, before they creep into the Hive, and I hold it beſt that the South part of the plancke board or ſtone, ſhould ſtand ſomewhat lower then the North part, for by that meanes no water, ſnow, or hayle, can runne into the Hive but will preſently fall off againe as it melteth. Laſtly, let the upper part of the mouth of the Hive bee but a little diſtance from the board, leaſt Snayles, Myce, or ſome other vermine creepe in, to the great danger and hurt of the Bees; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe you may let it be ſome three or foure inches broad in the Summer time, or elſe they will want conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient roome, to goe in and out at their pleaſure. But round about the Hive, except at the mouth let the Hive be dawbed up cloſe, with Clay, Cow-dung, or Morter, or rather a mixture of the two former with Aſhes or Sand.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>In every place where I travaile (except with you) I ſee them ſet upon a plancke, or board, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt cloſe one to another, wherefore then ſhould you
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:159996:14"/>place every one upon a ſeverall board, which, as I think, requireth much more planck or board, and alſo many ſtakes, with a great deale more labour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>I confeſſe, the manner you ſpeake of is moſt uſuall, eſpecially in this Country, but how hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full it is, might eaſily bee perceived, if thoſe that uſe it would diligently obſerve the ſame. For at ſome times by ſtanding ſo neere one another, they will undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly infect one another with their ſmell, eſpecially when any infection or diſeaſes happeneth amongſt them, as many times there doth. Secondly, they will bee the more ready to run one to another, and fight, and by that meanes the weaker are often oppreſſed by the ſtronger: Againe, their neerneſſe will hinder one another in ſwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming time, and when they do labour much. And laſtly, their coats cannot be taken off and on, as occaſion ſhall ſerve. And whereas you object, that it will ſpend more planck and board, that is not ſo, for the planck or board, need be no longer than the breadth of the Hive, only it muſt be wider, and ſo it muſt be the other wayes: now for a few more ſtakes, and the greater paynes, it is not worth the ſpeaking of, conſidering the benefit that will ariſe by it, prove it who that will.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>But do you hold it of neceſſity that the mouth or hole of the hive muſt ſtand towards the South?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>No verily, I would not have you take mee ſo, yet do I hold it abſolutely the beſt, both becauſe the Bees delight chiefly to fly that way, as alſo it is the hot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt; and the South ſunne in his heat will cauſe them the readilier to ſwarme: Nevertheleſſe, I have ſeene ſome ſtand towards the Weſt, that have done prettily well; but to the Eaſt, I hold it not good, and to the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:159996:15"/>North, much worſe; becauſe thoſe winds are moſt cold, and the Sunne hath leaſt power upon the hyves that ſtand with their mouthes that way.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Southern</hi> holdeth it not good to place them neere a river, or great pond, if it bee on the South part of them, becauſe (ſaith he) many of them will fall into the water, eſpecially in windy and tempeſtuous weather.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>If the river or pond bee very neere them, it is true, but if it be any diſtance off, as ſome furlong, or quarter of a mile, it mattereth not much, for then the Bees will fly high out of the danger of the ſame. Marry this I know to be eſpecially good, to pare the ground under and on the South ſide of them, ſome foure or five foot off, ſo that no graſſe or weeds may grow thereon, or elſe keepe the graſſe very ſhort, becauſe if the winde beat them down, they will get up much the ſooner: againe, mice, toads, ants, and wormes, will the leſſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort unto them to hurt and anoy them, becauſe they ſhall finde no covert or ſhelter there to hide them in.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>I thinke you ſayd that you would have them ſtand privately, as farre from noyſe or much reſort as conveniently may be, what ſhould be your reaſon for that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>I did ſay ſo indeed: for Bees of all other creatures can worſt away with any great noyſe, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the winter time, or in the night, for then they doe for the moſt part continually ſleepe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>How farre doe you thinke it convenient that one hive be placed and ſet from another, without danger of anoying his neighbour hive: and what forme would you obſerve in the placing of them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>I like beſt the ſetting them in rowes from
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:159996:15"/>Eaſt to Weſt, and being placed in that manner, I think if there be a foot, or halfe a pace between the outſides of the hyves, that is enough although where there is plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of roome, it ſhall not bee amiſſe to ſet them a yard a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder. But if you ſhall be conſtrayned to make more rowes than one, in this caſe you muſt place South and North at the leaſt ſome fifteen or ſixteen feet aſunder, before or behinde the other, both to have ſufficient roome upon any occaſion to go between them, as alſo to prevent any hurt that may happen amongſt them, by their over neerneſſe, in their going out and in. And thus much I think is ſufficient to inſtruct you, what ſhall bee needfull to be done concerning the removing and new placing of your Bees.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>But all this while I have heard you ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, what houſe or defence were fitteſt to bee made for your hyves, to keep them from wind, raine, and cold of the winter, for I cannot imagine that it were good to let the hyves ſtand bare and naked to the extremities of our cold winters and violent ſtormes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>No, nothing leſſe, for aſſure your ſelfe, the well defending them againſt the extremities of heat and cold, is one of the principall meanes of their welfare and increaſe, and therfore I will at large declare my opinion, which way I take to bee the beſt to defend them from the wind and weather. In many places (as you know) they uſe to make pentiſes or low houſes covered with board, thatch, or tyle, and ſo ſet them upon plancks un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſame, which indeed keepeth them from the raine, but neither from the heat of ſummer, nor cold of winter, for the hyves ſtanding naked, the heat or cold eaſily taketh hold of them, eſpecially any great and long froſt. Againe, the winds many times maketh a great
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:159996:16"/>noiſe in the hollowneſſe of theſe kinde of houſes, which ſore annoyeth the Bees in their reſt. And therefore with Mr. <hi>Southern</hi> I utterly miſlike thoſe kinds of houſes and pentiſes, as unprofitable and hurtfull unto Bees; yea I may boldly ſay, I never ſaw any great ſtore of Bees where they were kept in ſuch houſes. I will therefore ſhew two manner of Coating or Covering of hives, the one of Mr. <hi>Southerns</hi> invention, the other of mine owne; ſo that you may accept of which you like beſt; for either of them will ſerue for that purpoſe very well.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Southerns</hi> way is this, upon ſome rainy day, when the Bees are all at home, ſtop them up cloſe, thruſting in a little quill to giue them ayre, but not to let them come forth, for troubling you and themſelves; then take ſand &amp; Cowdung, or clay with Cowdung, tempered well to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and amongſt it temper good ſtore of ſtraw cut ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſhort; then take wheat, rye, or barly ſtraw, and lay a good deale of it upon the hyve, and upon that a good thickneſſe of the morter aforeſaid, and faſten it on, ſo hard as you can with a trewell, and ſo let it ſtand; then with a payre of Taylors ſheeres or other ſheeres, cut a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the ſtrawes that hang to low, round about the hive, and when the morter is dry, you may take it off or on at your pleaſure, and it will hold well together, and not breake, one of theſe (as ſaith Mr. <hi>Southern</hi>) will laſt two yeeres.</p>
               <p>Now thoſe of mine owne invention, I make thus, with wheat or rye ſtraw only, without any dawbing at all, in this manner; I take a pretty handfull of ſtraw, and towards the one end I bend it up againe, and there, within foure fingers of that end, I tie it faſt with rope-yarne, or good Elme peeling, then do I take another handfull, uſing it as before, and tie it faſt to the other
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:159996:16"/>with a ſingle knot between them, and ſo tie handfull af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter handfull, untill it will reach round about a hive: then do I tie the firſt handfull faſt to the laſt handfull, and put it upon an empty hyve, which I have of purpoſe ready by me; and when the lower end that is ſo faſtned together, is within ſome ſix inches of the ground, I ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all the upper ends of the ſtrawes together, and tie them all faſt together right above the crown of the hive, and as nigh it as I can, and then cut the ſtrawes away a foot above the place where you laſt tied it above the crown of the hive, and if any looſe or ſhort ſtrawes ſtick out, cut them away with a paire of ſheeres or ſuch like. And thus can I make as many as I liſt, and afterwards at my pleaſure in an evening or morning put them upon my hyves without troubling or moleſting my Bees at all. And if the lower end of my Coat come neere the planck or board whereon my Bees ſtand, as ſometimes they will do, I cut away the ſtraw right againſt the the mouth of the hive, for troubling the Bees in their paſſing out and in.</p>
               <p>And theſe kind of Coats will hold out raine, and keepe the Bees both from the heat in the Summer, and from the cold in Winter: and are done with little or no coſt, but onely a little paines taking twice or thrice in the yeere to renew ſuch as decay, or to make new for the ſwarmes in ſwarming time, for once or twice a yeere at the leaſt theſe muſt be viewed, and ſome of them amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded or renewed as need ſhall require.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>Although theſe Coats or coverings which you teach the making of, will defend the Bees as you ſay from the raine, heate, and cold, yet me thinke Mice, Flyes, and other vermine ſhould have great meanes to hide themſelues, yea and to breed alſo under them:
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:159996:17"/>which muſt needs be very perillous and hurtfull to the Bees, as both your ſelfe and all others that write of them confeſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>It is out of all doubt, that without looking unto once or twice in a moneth, it will fall out as you ſay: for no commodity is without his diſcommodity, and therefore to auoyd that, you muſt as I ſaid before, ſometimes lift up, or elſe take of their Coats, to ſee if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch offenſiue vermine be there, and to drive them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way or kill them if it be poſſible, and alſo to looke that it be not periſhed, ſo that the raine may runne in and hurt the Hive, for whoſoeuer will haue profit and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity of Bees, muſt ouerlooke them many times, and be viewing and repairing their wants as need ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, becauſe they require much more diligence, paines and induſtrie, then either expences or coſt. Notwitſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thoſe that loue them, it is rather to be tearmed a pleaſure and delight, then any irkſome or labourſome toyle at all, for what is it to ſpend a quarter of an houre amongſt them once or twice in a moneth or ſixe weeks, to overlooke them: which will ſerue although you had halfe a hundred Hiues.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>I doe not perceiue that they need any great paines, and that may be done at idle times for the ouerlooking of them. But one thing I muſt aske you more concerning their remoue. I find them now cloſe ſtopped up, except one little hole to the South not much bigger then will ſuffice for one Bee to come out at. When I remoue them ſhall I ſtop them up ſo cloſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>If you remoue them before the latter part of March, ſtop them up againe as cloſe as you found them, but alter that time, whether you remoue them or
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:159996:17"/>not, open their holes or mouths by little and little, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till it be mid Aprill or toward the beginning of May, for by that time you may open them as wide as ſhall be needfull, namely, as I haue ſaid elſewhere, ſome foure Inches at the leaſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>Why may I not open them as wide as need ſhall require at once, rather then to make ſo many workes of it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>You may doe ſo if you pleaſe, as many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers doe. Yet me thinke reaſon ſhould teach you, that as a man or woman hauing long time kept houſe and beene out of the ayre, if at their firſt comming abroad, they continue long therein, or be in a place where much ayre commeth, it will much offend them, and therefore ſuch are wont, by little and little to accuſtome themſelues, to the ayre: euen ſo, to let much ayre come into the Hiues upon a ſuddaine, at that time of the yeere. there then hapning after many cold blaſts, it cannot be but with great danger to the Bees, eſpecially if they be weake or feeble (as my ſelfe haue often ſeene) for a little thing helpeth or hurteth them at that time of the yeere. Againe at the time when you begin to open them, or within a while after, lift them eaſily cleane up from the board whereon they ſtand, and ſcrub and ſweepe away all the filth and ſharings of Combes or other things that you ſhall find vnder them, and then ſet them downe gently againe, for ſo ſhall they haue the more pleaſure to labour, and to repaire their Combes, thoſe noyous and filthy things being taken away.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>What if ſome of my Bees be poore and weake in the Spring time, ſhall I not ſeede them, or doe ſomewhat elſe to cheriſh relieue them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>Maſter <hi>Southerne</hi> doth utterly miſlike the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:159996:18"/>feeding of Bees, and alleadgeth ſome reaſon againſt it, namely, that old honey will make them to ſcowre and dye, or elſe the vſe of feeding will make them fall to rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing, and ſome other reaſons which for mine owne part I cannot abſolutely allow. For I haue ſeene Bees euen almoſt dead reuiued againe by a little feeding. Truth it is, it muſt be very warily done, and not often vſed but it an extremity. And when neceſſity ſhall conſtraine to doe it, you muſt take eſpeciall care that the other Bees come not vnto them, and therefore you muſt ſtop them vp ſauing a little hole to giue them breath, for otherwiſe the ſtronger Bees will fight with them for it, and not onely get it away but will kill them for it. And yet I muſt needs confeſſe that in the beginning of the Spring I haue ſeene more hurt then good come by feeding of them. But this I haue both ſeene and proued, that when in the latter end of May, or beginning of Iune a cold and Eaſterly wind hath continued long, or ſome conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall rainy weather hath hapned, the Bees haue firſt brought out the Drone ſpat, and after that their owne ſpat: and laſtly if it hath continued, haue died themſelues.</p>
               <p>In the yeere 1600, between the 17 of May and the 6 of Iune, I had twelue as goodly ſwarmes as euer I ſaw, and then there hapned a dry and cold Eaſt wind, that my ſwarmes for the moſt part periſhed, and my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Bees alſo hauing brought forth their brood or ſpat, began alſo to die themſelues, which I eſpying (by the great number I might ſee dead on the ground at the mouth of the hive) did a little feed them in the euenings and mornings, and it did preſently ſtrengthen them, that no more died. And euer ſince at that time of the yeere, I do diligently obſerue, that when I ſee them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to bring forth their ſpat, being forced thereto by
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:159996:18"/>any cold and dry weather, preſently to feed them, as I haue taught you; and whereas for the moſt part euery yeere ſince about that time, ſuch a like cold hath hapned, yet by this meanes I haue preuented the danger that would haue falne upon my Bees. But to feed them in February, March, or Aprill, is ſurely to no great purpoſe, without a great chance.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>Is there no courſe to be taken at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the ſpring, for the help and ſtrengthning of ſuch hives where the Bees be poore and weak?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Southern</hi> affirmeth that if about the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end of March, you perceiue the Bees in any of your hives to be faint, and that they go but ſlowly out and in, it is good to buy ſome <hi>Olibanum</hi> at the Apothecaries, and take a little of it bruiſed in a morter or ſuch like, and ſprinkle it upon a chafing-diſh of coales, and then hold that Hiue of Bees ouer it, that the ſmoake of the <hi>Olibanum,</hi> may aſcend vp into the Combes amongſt the Bees; and it is, ſaith he, much the better, if a little dryed Cow-dung bee mixed amongſt the <hi>Olibanum.</hi> This he conſtantly affirmeth will make them abide the ſharpeneſſe of the weather the better, and will ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en them very well. One groats worth of <hi>Olibanum</hi> he ſaith will ſerue forty Hiues, if need be. But how good it is for that purpoſe I never yet made tryall, nor any that ever I could learne, yet do I hold it very probable and likely to do good. The Bees being quickly ſet down againe, and well cloſed up; for this I forgot to tell you when you begin to open the mouthes of your Bees, if they be weake, open them the leſſe, and if ſtrong, you may be bold to open them the more:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>Well Sir, I ſuppoſe I am now ſufficiently inſtructed how to order my Bees in their remorſe, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:159996:19"/>after the ſame vntill the ſpring of the yeere, or begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of May. I pray you let me alſo underſtand what is further to be done, for then (if I miſtake not) beginneth the chiefe and principall time of their breeding, with the exportance of increaſe and profit by them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>It is very true, and therefore you muſt at this time (if not before) prouide hives, plancks, board, or ſtones, and all other things neceſſary for the receiuing and keeping of thoſe ſwarmes that you may probably expect.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>I haue ſeene (as I remember) ſome hives wrought with oſyers, or woodbind, or ſuch other like ſtuffe, and dawbed on the outſide with Cowdung and aſhes mixed together, but of late dayes I haue ſeen moſt of our hives made altogether of ſtraw, whether of theſe two faſhions do you hold the better?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>Diuers countries haue their ſeuerall faſhions, as well for the matter whereof they are made, as alſo for the manner and forme of their making. But in our country (as you ſay) the hives made of wickers or of ſtraw are principally in uſe; but whether of them is the better I will not peremptorily determine, becauſe I have ſeene Bees proſper and increaſe well in both: and I hold it not a materiall part of the well ordering of Bees, to uſe the one or the other, yet do I like beſt thoſe of ſtraw if they be well made, as the warmer and moſt agreeable to the nature of Bees, for we ſee that humble Bees, Waſpes, and other Flyes (whereof no doubt theſe are a kind) preſerue themſelues all the Winter, onely in the warmeneſſe of ſtraw, as in thatch and ſuch like.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>Is there then ſuch difference in the making, that you ſo much preferre the one before the other?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>Yea verily, and I had rather give ſeuen pence
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:159996:19"/>a peece for ſome, then foure pence a peece for other ſome, and yet are the beſt commonly as good cheape as the worſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>How then ſhall I know them aſunder, for I am like enough to buy the one as ſoone as the other?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>You ſhall eaſily know them aſunder, for the goodneſſe will ſoone appeare in the faſt and well bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of them, and in their good and handſome forme and faſhion. For if they be looſe and thinnely bound, they will not laſt, and beſides that, when they are laden with honey, the weight of it will preſſe downe the crowne of the Hives, and ſo marre the Combes and kill the Bees. Of ſtrawen Hives the beſt that ever I ſaw are made in <hi>Suffolke</hi> and <hi>Norfolke,</hi> were it not, that they make them for the moſt part ſomewhat to great.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>Doe you not like great Hives? me thinke they ſhould be the better, becauſe they will hold good ſtore of honey, and the Bees have the more ſtore of roome to worke in, and therefore ſhould caſt the greater ſwarmes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>It may peradventure ſeeme ſo indeed unto many, but experience and proofe doth declare the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, and therefore in any caſe avoid the buying of great Hives as hurtfull to the increaſe and proſperity of your Bees. For I aſſure you, I did never in my life ſee a great Hive yeeld any good increaſe, or almoſt come to any good: for if you put into a great Hive a ſwarme that is little or that ſwarmeth late, the roome is ſo large that they cannot any thing neere fill it the firſt yeere, by meanes whereof ſo much vacant place remaineth emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that it maketh all the Hive ſo cold in the Winter time, that it is great odds if it die not. And if you put in a forward ſwarme that is great, yea though it be a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:159996:20"/>duble or treble one (as often I have ſeene) and that it fill the hive, yet will it ſeldome or never caſt any ſwarms, as experience hath taught, and the reaſon ſeemeth to be, for that ſo much labour is ſpent in repairing of their Combes, renewing their brood, and filling ſo great a ſpace with neceſſaries, that they cannot, or need not ſend forth any Collonies, but have enough to doe, to keepe and furniſh their owne.</p>
               <p>Againe, let not your Hiues be over broad eſpecially at the Crowne, for in ſuch Hives Bees doe not delight, and therefore I had rather have my Hives high ſo they be narrow, then broad although they be ſhort. And thus much I ſuppoſe is ſufficient for the choice of your Hiues. I know that many preferre the Hiues that are made of Wheat ſtraw, before thoſe made of Rye ſtraw, as beſt liked and agreeable to the Bees, yet I could neuer perceiue any great difference for that matter, but like them as well as the other if their making be alike.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>But yet me thinke that the Hiues made of wickers ſhould be much more profitable in one reſpect, becauſe it muſt needs be granted that they will continue longer then thoſe made of ſtraw.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>Surely if the ſtraw Hiues be well made as I have ſeene ſome, and withall well preſerved from the weather, namely, from the Sunne and Raine as before is taught by coating of them, they will laſt many yeeres, and I thinke verily as long as the wicker Hives, and alſo they haue another commodity, for they are not ſo deare as the other, yet is all this nothing to the benefit that will grow if your Bees proſper well.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>When I have provided them according to your direction, what then ſhall I doe to them, for I haue ſeene ſome put ſtickes into their Hives faſtned to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:159996:20"/>both the ſides which I iudged they did to keepe the Combes, from ſtirring or falling out of the Hiues.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>You gueſſed rightly, for to that purpoſe they ſerue indeed. But firſt when you haue bought and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided your Hiues, you muſt with a knife or paire of ſheers picke and cut of all the ſtrawes ends that ſticke out within your Hives, and make them as ſmooth as is poſſible, for the Bees will like them much the better. Now concerning the ſticking of your Hives, ſundry men haue ſundry faſhions according as they conceit or like the ſame. But if your Hives be of ſtraw, I hold it good that you make a Crowne tree for them in this manner. Take a ſticke of Sallow or Haſell about the bigneſſe of a mans thumbe, let it be a foote long or ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more, then cleave it croſſe wayes from one end untill you come within a handfull or thereabouts of the other end, and no farther: then bend every quarter a ſeverall way, cutting off the ſharpe edge in the midſt of every of them: Then muſt you put the end that is not cleft to the crowne of the Hive, and bending every of the parts a ſeverall way, ſticke them into the ſides of the Hive, that they may force the upper uncleft end hard to the crowne of the Hive. But if the Hive haue a little hole in the crowne (as the moſt ſtraw Hives haue) then cut the upper end of your ſaid crowne tree where it is not cleft ſmall enough to goe thorow it a little way, leaving a ſhoulder on the inſide to ſtay it and this is good to keep the crowne of Hives from ſagging downewards (as they will doe except your Hiues be excellent good) when they are heauy laden with honey, but this you muſt obſerue, that if you put your crowne-tree through the crowne of your Hive, you muſt make it ſomewhat the longer as experience of it ſelfe will teach you. Laſtly,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:159996:21"/>take a ſmaller ſtick, and cleaue it cleane through in the midſt, cutting both the parts flat and ſmooth, and put them croſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wiſe into the hive, within foure fingers of the board they ſhall ſtand upon; and this is all the ſtick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that ſhall need for any hive, only this you muſt note, that the foure lower ends of the crown tree ſhould come and ſtick within halfe a foot at the leaſt of the lower part of the hive.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>Do you not uſually dreſſe and trim your hives with ſome hony, or other ſweet liquor, before you put any ſwarm into them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>It is a common matter ſo to do indeed, yet if the hive bee new and ſweet, I hold it not materiall to do any ſuch thing, but the Bees will like it well enough without it. Neuertheleſſe, becauſe it is a thing that may help thoſe that bee old, and ſomewhat unſauory, and cannot hurt any, I will ſhew you what my ſelfe and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers others uſe to do in this caſe. Gather ſome fennell, mallowes, or other ſweet herbs, and dip them in fayre water, drink, or ſweet wort, putting a little hony into them, if you haue it, and ſprinkle or rub well the inſide of your hives and ſticks, or if you haue no hony, do it with any of the former, or with milk that is ſweet, and it will ſuffice. But this kinde of dreſſing would not bee done untill you are ready to put the ſwarme into it, or a very little time before.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mr. Southern</hi> ſaith, that if your Bees bee froward, ſo that they will not tarry in any hive, then it is good to take your hive whether it be old or new, and pull out the ſticks, and put therein two handfuls of bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, peaſe, or mault, yet the laſt (ſaith he) is the beſt, and let a Hog, Sow, or pig eat it out of the hive, turning the hive as hee eateth, with your hands, that the froth hee
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:159996:21"/>maketh may remaine on the hive, then wipe the hive lightly againe with a cloth, and put in your ſticks as before, and hive your Bees againe, and they will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly tarry in the ſame, as he ſaith.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>True it is, he affirmeth ſo indeed, but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be ſo or no, I know not, becauſe I never made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny triall thereof, for I neuer had any ſwarme that I could not make take liking of one hive or other that I had by mee, and therefore I neuer trouble my ſelfe to make triall of <hi>Mr. Southerns</hi> experiment; yet do I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that hee would not ſo confidently haue written it without ſome good proofe, and alſo the knowledge thereof, if it be true, is worth the noting, and the triall alſo if occaſion ſerue: and thus much I hold ſufficient for your inſtruction in the dreſſing and trimming of your hives.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>Well Sir, I thank you for your paines, I would now intreat you to let me underſtand about what time of the yeere I may in likelihood expect ſwarmes, becauſe of giuing attendance and watching of them, as I beleeue we muſt in ſwarming times.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>Concerning the time of the yeere when Bees accuſtomably begin to ſwarme, there can no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine rule bee giuen, becauſe the forwardneſſe of the Spring, warmneſſe of the weather, and buſineſſe of the Bees may make them ſwarme much ſooner than other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they would do. Yet do I hold it good to haue all neceſſary things ready by the midſt of May at the far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt, it not before; for then euery day you may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably looke for ſwarmes, if the other circumſtances be fauourable; and therefore you muſt from that time for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, ſo long as their ſwarming time indureth, diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly watch and looke unto them. Now concerning the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:159996:22"/>of your ſwarmes, thus much; when any hive be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth to ſwarme, haue a good eye upon them where they light or ſettle, yet ſo that you trouble or moleſt them not, with running to and fro amongſt them: and when they are ſetled, take your hive made ready as you are taught before, and put them into it in this manner; If they bee ſetled upon the bough of a tree, buſh, hedge, or ſuch like, that you can put your hive under them, lay firſt a fanne or board right under them, with a ſtick or twaine upon it, for keeping the hive that it ſtand not too cloſe unto it, ſo that the Bees cannot go out and in, and then turne your hive upward, and ſhake as many of the Bees into the ſame as you can, and ſet it gently upon the ſaid board or fanne, and ſpread a ſheet ouer the hive, to keep away the heat of the Sunne, yet ſo as ſome one place be open for the Bees to finde the way to the hive, and to work and make cleane the hive. But if any of them cluſter againe about or neer the place from whence they were ſhaken, ſhake them off againe, or elſe ſweepe them off with a wing, and lay Mayweed or wormwood about the place, and they will forſake it, and follow the reſt of their fellowes into the hive. But if your ſwarm light ſo low in a hedge, or ſuch like place, that you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not put your hive under them, nor ſhake them into it, nor ſweep them into it with a wing, then may you ſet your hive ouer them, ſo that it touch the upper part of of them, and by laying Mayweed or wormwood under them, and about them, you ſhall make them run up into the hive without any other trouble, ſtill following them with the Mayweed or wormwood, as they go up from it, though peraduenture it will bee ſomewhat long ere they be all gone up, yet they will go up at the laſt, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſtirring.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:159996:22"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>In ſome places I haue ſeene, that they would not hive their ſwarmes untill late in the euening, and me think it ſhould bee a very good way, for at that time there is not ſo much danger of ſtinging, as in the heat of the day, as alſo they will bee then hived very quietly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>By that meanes they are in danger to loſe many ſwarmes; for I haue many times ſeene ſwarmes that haue ſetled themſelues very well, and within an houre or two after, for want of hiving, haue gone back againe to the hive from whence they came, yea, and ſometimes haue taken their flight cleane away, which might haue been preuented in time, if they had preſently been hived. Again, where there are ſtore of Bees, there will ſomtimes happen three, foure, or fiue ſwarmes in a day, and within a very ſmall time one of another, if they ſhould not bee hived ſoon after they are ſetled, they would go all or the moſt part of them together, which ſometimes can hardly bee preuented, do the beſt a man can.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>But all this while I heare you ſpeak nothing of the ringing of baſons, or ſuch like, which I haue often heard when a ſwarme is up, or in riſing; it ſeemeth you are of Mr. <hi>Southerns</hi> mind in that thing, for hee ſeemeth to miſlike it much.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>Yea verily, for it is a very ridiculous toy, and moſt abſurd inuention; and I aſſure you, if it worketh any effect, it is rather hurtfull than profitable to the Bees. For as I ſaid before, all great noiſe doth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly diſquiet and hurt them; and ſo farre am I from thinking that it will hinder them from flying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, that I verily beleeue it may be a principall cauſe to make them go away the rather, beſides other hurt in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:159996:23"/>diſquieting of them, which maketh them fierce and waſpiſh, for my ſelfe haue had aboue forty ſwarmes in a yeere, and haue not loſt one of them, when my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours having a farre leſſe number, and uſing this kinde of ringing and jangling, yet haue loſt diuers.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>I heard you ſay, that when diuers ſwarmes ariſe together, or preſently one after another, namely, before the other be hived, that it is ods but they will go together: what meanes haue you to preuent that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>The beſt way is, not to ſuffer two or more ſwarmes to ariſe together, and that is done in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; as ſoone as one ſwarme is riſen or riſing, mark well your other hives, and if you ſee any begin to ſwarme, take a table napkin, or other cleane linnen cloth, and ſtop up the mouth or hole of the hive as cloſe as may be, laying a brickbat or ſtone upon it, untill the other ſwarme bee put into the hive, and all quiet: then pull a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the cloth, and it will preſently ſwarme, or within a very ſhort time after. And thus may you let them out one after another, at your pleaſure, though you have halfe a dozen that will ſwarm in a day. And if you uſe not this meanes, when one ſwarm ariſeth before the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer is cleane hived, you may do thus, (for if two riſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, there is no help except they part of themſelves, which is very rare.) But in the other caſe, when you ſee the latter ſwarm go to the former, and are almoſt lighted about and upon the hive, and that there is a good part of the former ſwarm gone into the hive, take that hive cleane away as ſecretly as you can, and carry it ſome eight or ten rods from that place at the leaſt, firſt hauing ſet an empty hive where it ſtood, and often times I have ſeene the latter ſwarm go quietly into it, and haue both done very well, yet ſometimes they will finde out one
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:159996:23"/>another, and go together do what you can. And that
I take to be when all the maſter Bees happen to go into
one hive, ſo that the other hive hath none, without
whom (as I think) they cannot liue and proſper, but of
that I will ſpeak elſewhere, when I ſhall declare the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
of breeding and gouernment of Bees.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mr. Southern</hi> ſeemeth to miſlike the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
many ſwarmes of one hive; what ſay you to that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>That hive which hath caſt mee one good
ſwarm, I acknowledge to haue done well for that yeere;
yet although it yeeld me another, the ſtock may do well
enough, but the laſt ſwarm is in hazard, except it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen
ſoone; but if a ſtock ſwarm three or foure ſwarmes
in a yeere (as ſomtimes I haue ſeene) both the ſtock and
the latter ſwarmes are all in great danger to die the next
winter, except you put two or three ſuch ſwarmes toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;
and for the ſtock, the beſt way is, to driue it at
Bartholomew tide, for in moyſt ſummers you ſhall haue
ſome hives will almoſt ſwarm out all their Bees, as my
ſelfe haue had.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>Will Bees ſwarm moſt in moyſt and wet
ſummers?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, without all queſtion, and thereof com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
that prouerb, that in moyſt yeeres there is plenty
of Bees, and in dry yeares plenty of hony; yet may
there be good ſtore of both in one and the ſame yeere:
for if May and Iune prove ſtormy, you ſhall haue plenty
of ſwarmes, and if Iuly proue dry, you ſhall haue good
ſtore of hony.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>What doe you thinke ſhould be the reaſon of this?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>Experience doth proue it to be ſo, yet I take the reaſon to be, for that the Bees both ſpat faſter and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:159996:24"/>preſerve and nouriſh their brood the better, by the moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture that falleth in thoſe times, which in dry weather they cannot ſo well get, except ſuch as is in part corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted being mixed with other waters. And this I take to be the cauſe that Bees will come abroad ſo faſt preſently after a ſtorme of raine, and againe want of raine and dewes at that time of the yeere maketh them to looſe their brood as I have before declared.</p>
               <p>Now for honey it is out of all doubt that there is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any ſtore untill Iuly, or towards the latter part of Iune, and without queſtion drie weather is beſt for that, Becauſe it is nothing elſe but a gummy and thicke dew made by the influence of the Starres, or rather cauſed by the providence of the divine power, for the profit and delight of man falling from heauen at that time of the yeere, (being digeſted and made perfect by the nature of the Bees (created for that purpoſe,) which ſtormes and raine will diſſolue and waſh cleane away: And this is ſo apparent that every man of any obſervation may mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly perceiue. For when there is greateſt ſtore of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, ſo that it is ſenſibly to be felt upon leaves and flowers, if there happen any great ſtorme, or raine of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny continuance, preſently after there will bee no ſuch thing perceived, but it will be cleane gon and waſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. Againe, marke the Bees when they gather ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney faſteſt (as may be perceived eaſily in the morning, by a deaw and moyſture, that will bee at the mouth of the Hive and alſo by the great ſmell of honey if you come neere in the evening) yet if a raine happen to fall of any quantity (as I ſaid before) you ſhall ſee no ſuch deaw the morning following, nor ſome two or three mornings after, although it be faire weather againe, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the deaw being thickned and ſweetned by the heate,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:159996:24"/>haue againe obtained the former quallity, but of this more hereafter. See <hi>Southerne</hi> to take Bees out of a hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
tree.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>You ſpake of putting two or three ſwarmes together, I pray you how doe you that? For I have heard ſome affirme that they will fight and kill one another if they be put together, and can hardly be made to agree.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>It is then becauſe it is unskilfully done, for otherwiſe they will either not ſtrive at all, or elſe very little, and the manner is in this ſort.</p>
               <p>When you have a ſecond ſwarme or caſtling (as ſome call it) put it into a Hiue as you doe the reſt, and ſet it up with your other, and when you have another like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it that you would put to it, Hive it alſo in a Hive by it ſelfe and ſo let it ſtand untill the evening; then at night when it is darke, take a Fanne or board and lay it by your firſt ſecond ſwarme to which you would put the other, laying a ſmall ſticke or two upon it to keepe the Hive for ſtanding too cloſe to the board or Fanne: laſtly, take your later ſwarme and carry it thither, and with your hand iumpe it downe upon the Fanne or board ſo hard, that all the Bees in it may fall out upon the ſame, then take your other Hive wherein your firſt ſwarme is, and gently ſet it over them, and the Bees will preſently runne into it, but if any happen to creepe up on the outſide of the Hive (as many times ſome will doe) with a wing ſweepe them downe and they will runne into the Hive alſo: and ſo it being done when it is late in the night, there will be no great ſturre or fighting, and by the morning all will be agreed and quiet. Whereas if you put them together in the day time or any other manner (that ever I could ſee) they will indeed fight and kill one another, to the great danger of them both.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:159996:25"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>I promiſe you I like this manner of putting them together well, and I haue not heard of he like, but I pray you why may not the former ſwarm bee put to the later, as well as the later to the former?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>You may do ſo alſo if you pleaſe, but I like the other the better for this cauſe, peraduenture you ſhall not haue another ſecond ſwarm ſometime three or foure dayes, or a weeke after your former, and by that time your firſt ſwarm hath clenſed their hive, and wrought ſome pretty ſtore of combes, yea, and perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture gathered ſome hony alſo, which would be loſt if you ſhould put them out of their hive, to the other, whereas the other haue gathered little or nothing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſwarmed but the day before.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>That is very true indeed, you haue fully ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied me for this. But I pray you, is it certaine, that by this meanes the Bees will live and proſper better than they would haue done, being in two ſeuerall hiues?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>Yea verily, for all experience doth teach, that very few ſecond ſwarmes will liue ouer a yeere, if they be not ſwarmed ſoone in the yeere, (which ſeldom or neuer hapneth) except you uſe them in this manner; by putting two or three ſwarmes together, and then they will do as well as a firſt ſwarme, although it bee great and good, as my ſelfe haue had good proofes and experience.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>But as I think, a few Bees ſhould need but a little food, and many Bees much food, and therefore it ſhould not bee the number of the Bees that ſhould make them thriue or liue the better, but the proportion of the food they gather, according to the number of the Bees that are to liue upon the ſame, bee they many or few, whereas multitudes many times make ſcarcity, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:159996:25"/>bringeth danger to all the company.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>You haue ſome probability for that you ſay, but yet it is not altogether ſo in his caſe. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it bee manifeſt that Bees cannot live without honey, which is their food, yet is warmth an eſpeciall matter unto them in the winter, which is the onely time when they can ſuffer want; and therefore when there is a great companie, they fill the Hive or neere unto it, and ſo keepe one another the warmer: whereas if there be but few, ſo great a place remaineth emptie, and having gathered but little they eaſily take cold. Whereon the contrarie we ſee that many hands make light worke, ſo that ſuch a multitude eaſily gather ſome good quantitie of waxe and honey to furniſh the Hive, and to keepe them warme: and although many of them happen to die, yet ſome good number remaineth alive vntill breeding time. Whereas if there be but a few, and ſome of them die, the number remaining is not able to doe any thing, and ſo will either die alſo or elſe forſake the Hive.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>One thing I will here aske you while I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member it: doe you coat your Hives at this time of the yeere, or doe you tarry till winter time when cold wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther approacheth?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>When you have any ſwarme that is ſet up, Coate it as ſoone as you can, for the heate of the Sunne may otherwiſe doe it much hurt, for although any great heate of the Sunne hurteth old ſtocks very much if they have no defence, yet doth it hurt ſwarmes a great deale more, and will make their waxe and honey to melt much ſooner, as in all reaſon may eaſily be coniectured becauſe their Combes are ſoft and tender, and their honey farre thinner then that in the old ſtocks.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:159996:26"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>I have not yet heard you declare how one might know when a Hiue will ſwarme; is there no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine rules for that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>No ſurely that euer I could perceiue, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially before a Hiue hath once ſwarmed, but afterwards if it will ſwarme againe, you ſhall know it if you goe in the evening, for you ſhall heare a touting in manner like the ſounding of a Bewgle horne amongſt the Bees.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>I haue ſeene in ſome places where I haue beene, that their Bees haue exceedingly lyen out upon the Hiue and board, is not that an apparant ſigne that they will very ſhortly ſwarme.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>Experience doth teach that when Bees doe lie out as you ſpeake of, it is often very long ere they ſwarme, yea and ſometimes not at all that yeere: and I take the reaſon or cauſe to be two-fold, one is when they are oppreſſed with heat either by the force of the Sunne or ſome other matter, ſo that they cannot well abide in the Hive, which hindereth their breeding, and alſo they coole themſelues abroad, and therefore care not for ſwarming: another cauſe I take to be when there is good ſtore of hony which they are loath to forſake, &amp; ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue without for the moſt part rather then to ſwarme, yet commonly when a Hive maketh a great noiſe and ſtirre in the euening, it is a great probabilitie that it will ſwarme ere it belong.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>I remember, Maſter <hi>Southerne</hi> ſaith that if two ſwarmes happen to goe together, they will not be ſo good as one. For (ſaith he) although they will tarry together, yet there will be contempt betweene them, ſo that they will not thrive nor proſper.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>That is nothing but a meere conceit of his without probability or ground, for I hope he taketh not
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:159996:26"/>Bees to be reaſonable creatures to know one another a long time after there comming together, to be of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther breed. And although that Bees and other unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable creatures meeting with others of the ſame kind, will often at the firſt ſight ſtrive and fight amongſt themſelues: yet being a little accuſtomed together they agree well enough without thinking how they came to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, or contending for ſuperioritie. For elſe it muſt needs be granted that they ſhould haue memorie which is a part of reaſon, whereof all creatures (except man) are uncapable of. And for mine owne part I can aſſure you, that alwayes I have ſeene by experience that they have liked and done very well. Yet this I haue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſeene, that when two ſwarmes have gone together of their owne accord, that one of the Maſter Bees hath beene found dead upon the board or Fanne whereon the Hive hath ſtood, which hath beene killed (as it ſeemeth) by the reſt of the Bees, to avoide confuſion in their go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, which muſt needs happen by multitude of Governours.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe you heere ſpeak of maſter Bees, you put me in mind to aske your opinion concerning them. For Maſter <hi>Southerne</hi> ſeemeth to denie that there are any ſuch kind of Bees (contrary to the opinion of all that euer (I thinke) wrote of them) and affirmeth that Bees are led either (as other creatures) by thoſe that put themſelues formoſt, or elſe by the Drones who are more ſtronger and luſtier then the other Bees, and doe make the greater noiſe which, ſaith he, the other follow.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>He ſeemeth to be of that opinion indeed, wherein he ſheweth exceeding ignorance in that thing, and I therefore imagine that hee never ſaw Maſter Bee.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:159996:27"/>
               <p>And yet me think had he no other reaſon to perſwade him but the very maſter Bees houſes or cels, hee might well haue ſuppoſed them to bee a different kinde of Bees from the other, both conſidering the different faſhion in the making thereof, as alſo the place apt and fit for command.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>Is there any ſuch great difference in the maner of the making and placing of their houſes that ſhould declare ſo apparant a difference betweene them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>Yea for certayne very much: for all the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Bees have their houſes or cells ioyned together in an uniforme order without any difference, as every one can place himſelfe, which we call the combes. But the houſes or cells of the maſter Bee, are not placed like the other, nor have the like faſhion, but are made by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves long, thicke, and much ſtronger then the other. Beſides that, they are not ranged amongſt the reſt, but are placed at the paſſages of the Bees, as they goe to and fro up and into the hives: in ſuch ſort as a man may well perceive, are moſt fit to overſee and command what is needfull to be done; but I will more at large anſwer that Mr. <hi>Southerns</hi> objections in another place.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>Well Sir, then I will propound no more queſtions concerning that at this time, yet I remember you were of this opinion with <hi>Mr. Southern,</hi> that many ſwarmes were not good out of one hive; what meanes is there to preuent it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>Surely in ſome yeeres, and of ſome hives there is little remedy for it; neuertheleſſe, my order is, that when I haue had one ſwarm of a hive, within a while after, if it be in May or Iune (for if the firſt ſwarm bee afterwards, there is no great likelihood of a ſecond or third ſwarm) I hoiſt or lift up the ſtock the thickneſſe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:159996:27"/>(or ſometimes) the breadth of a brick, and ſo lay brick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bats under the hive round about, except at the mouth; prouided that they go no further under the hive, than the thickneſſe of the ſides; then do I dawbe it well up againe, and make a handſome mouth, with a peece of a trencher, or little board. And this will make them more roome, and cauſe them to bee buſie in filling the empty place up againe, ſo that it is a great chance if they ſwarm any more that yeere: <hi>I</hi> haue ſeene in <hi>Suffolk</hi> and <hi>North-folk</hi> things made of ſtraw for that purpoſe, which are very good, but wee haue them not here abouts. Now if the hive bee hoiſted before, then there is no remedy that I know, but that they will ſwarm as often as they liſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mr. Southern, I</hi> think, ſpeaketh of ſuch a matter, but he would haue the hoiſting taken away, and the hive ſet down again towards the winter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>He doth indeed, and <hi>I</hi> cannot but wonder at his error, for <hi>I</hi> neuer ſaw any hive hoiſted up in my life, if it were done any thing ſoone in the yeere, namely in May or Iune, but the Bees did worke downe to the board or planck they ſtood on againe; and then euery man may conjecture, that the combes would be preſſed and thruſt together by taking away of the brickbats, or other hoiſting, and many of the Bees killed, as alſo the place would be ſtopped up for others to go to and fro, and much of the hony preſſed out with the weight of the hive and hony.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>Surely in reaſon a man would imagine no leſſe, and therefore I think he muſt needs be deceiued in this. And yet I ſuppoſe he holdeth another opinion as abſurd as this; and that is, that hee would not haue the Drones killed, who all the world hold to bee enimies to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:159996:28"/>the Bees, deuourers of their food that they ſhould liue by in the winter, and ſuch as altogether do liue by the labours of others.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>But therein you deceiue your ſelfe, for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though, I confeſſe, I am not fully of that opinion with him in this matter, yet do I hold alſo that the Drones are neceſſary and helpfull to the Bees, ſo long as they exceed not a due proportion (much like to our Lawyers) but let their number grow to great (as often it doth) and they will indeed deuoure the ſubſtance of the Bees (as the Lawyers of the Commonwealth) and finally bring it to deſtruction. And therefore Nature hauing taught the Bees to perceiue this thing, hath alſo armed them to kill in the later part of the Summer, when they increaſe too faſt, ſo many of them as ſhall bee a burthen unto them. I would reaſon would teach us by their example to prouide a remedy againſt the unmeaſurable multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of our Lawyers, which I dare boldly ſpeak, haue the ſame quality in our State that Drones haue in a hive, namely to be good if they exceed not proportion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>Then you would not kill any Drones your ſelfe, but let them alone to the pleaſure of the Bees to kill or ſaue as many as they liſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>I am in part of that minde indeed, yet haue I ſeene ſome hiues ſo full of Drones, as I think verily that the Bees were not able to ouermaſter them without ſome help: and therefore in ſuch a caſe I would haue you with your finger or knife (ſtanding cloſe by the hiue, that you ſee ſurcharged ouermuch with them) kill a good many of them as they come out and in amongſt the Bees: and hauing made a good beginning, you ſhall ſee the Bees go forwards and performe the reſt: marry to do it with a Spark leape or engine of rods, I utterly
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:159996:28"/>miſlike. For ſo you may kill the maſter Bees, or ſome of his brood, inſtead of Drones, as ſometime I haue ſeene: and againe, by that meanes all or the moſt part of the Drones may be taken, which is alſo hurtfull, for this aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure your ſelfe, you ſhall neuer ſee a hive proſper well, be it a ſwarm or an old ſtock, untill there bee ſome good number of Drones in it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>Do you not remember that <hi>Mr. Southern</hi> ſcoffeth at <hi>Mr. Hill</hi> for a deuice he hath written, how to deſtroy Drones, namely by pulling off ſome of his legs, and one of his wings, and to let him go into the hive againe, for the Bees (ſaith he) will fall upon all the reſt and kill them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>As fantaſticall as <hi>Mr. Hill</hi> is, that conceit of his is not altogether ſo abſurd as <hi>Mr. Southern</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it. For this you ſhall well perceiue, if you diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerue it, that about mid Iuly or ſomewhat after, at which time Bees begin to kill their Drones, if ſome hive do not then fight with, and kill their Drones, do but maime or kill ſome two, three, or foure, and lay them upon the board at the mouth of the hive, or put them into the ſame a little; and this very thing will begin the fray and contention between them, and they will kill them ſooner then peraduenture otherwiſe they would haue done: Neuertheleſſe, except it bee about that time of the yeere, it will nothing at all preuaile, and that might deceiue <hi>Mr. Hill,</hi> who indeed like a forward Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, publiſhed his experiments at the firſt ſight, as he did the ſetting of Wheat, and many other phantaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call toyes, without due proofe, good probability, or ſure ground of reaſon. But to our killing of Drones: I hold it the beſt way to let the Bees themſelues to execute their juſtice upon them whom nature hath taught to do that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:159996:29"/>which ſhall be for their owne good, as well in this as in ſundry other matters, as experience doth well teach.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>Vntill what time of the yeere will Bees ſwarm?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>Bees do commonly ceaſe from ſwarming about the fifteenth of Iuly, yet haue I had ſome in the beginning of Auguſt, notwithſtanding when they hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen ſo late in the yeere, they are nothing worth, except it bee to driue and to take that little hony and wax that they haue gathered, about September, and to kill the Bees.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>How long may it be ere a hive ſwarmeth, and yet the ſwarm in likelihood may liue?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>I cannot giue any certain rule for that, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the goodneſſe of the yeere, and greatneſſe of the ſwarm may make much to the furtherance of the ſame: yet haue I ſundry yeeres obſerued, that thoſe ſwarmes which hapned at or before the fifteenth of Iuly, haue done well: but neuer later in all the time of my obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation amongſt Bees: and yet notwithſtanding it muſt bee underſtood of ſuch as are either firſt ſwarmes, or where two or three are put together as before is taught.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>Then it ſeemeth to me by that which you haue ſaid, that all ſuch ſwarmes as happen at or before mid Iuly, are in probability likely to liue, and ſuch one may keepe for ſtore or elſe not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>The time of their ſwarming (as I ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) cannot bee giuen as a certaine rule, to judge by, whether they will liue or die untill the next yeere: For I haue had ſwarmes about the eighth or tenth of Iuly, that haue proſpered better than ſome that were ſwarmed a month before; for it is with them as with all other
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:159996:29"/>creatures, where many times the likelieſt and moſt good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in ſhew or expectancy, proue worſt in the end, and thoſe that ſeeme little or nothing worth, proſper and do well: Yet I muſt needs confeſſe, this is extraordinary and rare. Neuertheleſſe, it is worthy of obſeruation, becauſe without it you may preſume of the goodneſſe of aſwarm according to the time of the ſwarming, which without other conſiderations may be a falfe rule.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>What rule is there then to bee giuen to know which are likely to liue, and which for certaine will die: becauſe (as I think) if there bee no probable hope that a hive will live, it is better to take their hony, than to loſe both hony and Bees alſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>That is moſt ſure, and therefore many haue endeuoured to preſcribe rules for the knowledge of the ſame; amongſt whom Mr. <hi>Southern</hi> is one, who hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that except a hive haue fiue quarts of hony or neere thereunto, it muſt needs die the next winter fallowing. But I am farre from this opinion; for in ſome wet Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers ſcarce one hive amongſt halfe a dozen, will ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo much hony as hee ſpeaketh of. And I do verily beleeue, that I haue ſeene ſwarmes liue ouer a yeere that haue not had a pottle of hony, nor yet ſcarce three pints in it. But I muſt needs confeſſe, that there is great ods and difference in ſome yeeres, yea almoſt halfe in halfe, and that conſiſteth eſpecially in the goodneſſe and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perateneſſe of the Spring following: becauſe from ſome fortnight or three weekes after Michaelmas, untill about mid February, Bees for the moſt part do continually ſleepe, and ſo do ſpend but little of their food, ſo that at that time of the yeere foule weather doth them no hurt, if they bee kept dry and well ſtopt up; but rather warm weather which maketh them come abroad, and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:159996:30"/>become hungry. Now about the midſt of February, the Spring being at hand, and the Sunne about noone giuing ſome forcible heat, they will then begin, if the weather be faire and warm, to look abroad, and to play about, eſpecially if the Sunne ſhine: yet do they gather nothing worth the while, untill towards Aprill, nor then neither except the Spring bee forwards, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their hardneſſe, if any bee, commeth in now, and that is two manner of wayes. The one is a late Spring, by which meanes it is long ere Bees beginne to gather. The other, which is worſe, is when the Spring time fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth out ſometimes wet, and ſometimes dry, now hot, and now cold, for heat wakeneth them from ſleep, and maketh them to come abroad, and after that cold pinch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them. Againe, wet and warm weather maketh them to drink much water, and dry and cold weather com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming after it maketh them to ſcowre, and ſo to die.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>What manner of Spring do you hold beſt for Bees?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>As I ſaid before, the forward Spring that is temperate. But if there happen any exceſſe, I do pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre a dry Spring before a wet. For alwayes in dry Springs although they bee lateward, I haue ſeene Bees do very well, and ſwarm timely, which I could neuer perceiue in an ouer wet Spring. But to anſwer your former queſtion, for the making of my choice of thoſe ſwarmes I would keepe: About mid Auguſt, or ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what after, I take a view of all my ſwarmes, eſpecially of thoſe that ſwarmed after the eighth or tenth of Iuly, (for the other if I ſee them worke luſtily, I make no doubt of:) now theſe I lift up gently with my hands from the board whereon they ſtand, and if they be any thing heauy, and haue about three quarters or more fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:159996:30"/>the hive with combes, I have great hope in them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>Have you no certaine weight that you goe by in your choyſe of thoſe that you ſave?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>No truely, but experience herein muſt bee your beſt rule, let them all affirme what they liſt: yet I muſt confeſſe, I would not ſave any by my will, except I did thinke them to have a pot of honey at the leaſt in them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>Well Sir, I ſuppoſe I am ſufficiently now inſtructed about the ordering of Bees, and what times and ſeaſons are beſt and moſt pleaſing unto them. For if I miſtake not, you would have the ſpring of the yeere (which I ſuppoſe you meane to be the months of March and Aprill) to be warme and ſomewhat dry, that they might be doing betimes, and as moſt agreeable unto them. The latter part of May and Iune, you like beſt to be ſomewhat moyſt, with warme ſhowres, becauſe the Bees doe breed and ſwarme beſt in ſuch weather. But Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly you deſire ſhould be hot and dry, for that as you ſay, cauſeth great ſtore of honey.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>Yea verily, and the yeere falling out in this manner, where Bees are well looked to and ordered as here is taught: they will in all probability bring forth great increaſe, and yeeld much profit to thoſe that keepe them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>Yet all this while you have ſaid nothing concerning the driving of hyves, about which I have heard ſo great variety of opinions, as namely whether it be beſt to drive them, and yet to ſave the Bees, or elſe to take as much honey as one can, and burne the Bees. I pray you ſhew me your conceit and iudgement in this alſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>You muſt underſtand that in the driving of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:159996:31"/>Bees, conſiſteth all the profit that the owner maketh by the keeping of them, and therefore it behoveth you, and all men that will keepe Bees, ſo to doe, as you may make the moſt profit by them that you can deviſe, with the leaſt hurt and deſtruction to the Bees. And this I hope no man of underſtanding will deny. Now, Sir, it remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth for me to argue and prove whether of theſe two waies you ſpeake of, will performe or come neereſt that matter, and this is the thing (as I imagine) that you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to know.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>Yea without all queſtion, that is my deſire indeed.</p>
               <p>To deliver my opinion in few words, I hold that to drive them about <hi>Bartholomew</hi> tide, or a little after, and ſo to burne or kill the Bees, is ſimply the beſt and moſt profitable, both for the owner, and the increaſe of his Bees. Now my reaſons to prove the ſame, I will briefly declare. Firſt, the time of the yeere to drive them in, when there is any hope to ſave them, muſt needs be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Mid ſummer, or before, and then there is great ſtore of ſpatt and young Bees, who are altogether di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed by that meanes. Againe, the Bees are ſo diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged by the loſſe of that which they have gathered, that they have almoſt no heart to labour againe, and that may be made apparant by this. For as I ſaid before, I have ſeene many ſwarmes that came at mid Iuly, that have proſpered and done well, but never any that were driven ſo late, almoſt by tenne dayes, (which is a great matter at that time of the yeere) furthermore, if you drive them at that time, you are ſure to have ſmall ſtore of honey, which is the principall end of your driving of them: and laſtly, which is worſt of all, theſe Bees being thus robbed as it were of their proviſion, and made unfit
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:159996:31"/>or unable to furniſh themſelues againe, for the moſt part fall to robbing of others, and ſo not onely worke idlely or elſe ceaſe from gathering themſelues, but doe much hurt to their neighbours, eſpecially to thoſe that have gathered leaſt, whoſe Hives being in part empty, they have the more roome to get in amongſt them. And by this meanes are the cauſe of the loſſe and hurt of more than themſelues: as whoſoever will diligently obſerue them ſhall well perceive the ſame.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>If it be thus dangerous to themſelues, and hurtfull to others, I wonder that ſo many doe accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mably drive their Hives after that manner, yet have I hard ſome hold opinion that it is great pitty to kill the Bees that have laboured ſo for us.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>A fooliſh cuſtome and a fond conceit will often prevaile more with many, than either reaſon or experience. For now and then peradventure a Hive may be driven after that manner which doth liue, and therefore they will adventure againe upon the like haz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard, hoping they may live alſo, which I dare undertake ſcarce one among five doth: and that peradventure may be with the deſtruction of two or three other Hives that they have robbed, which is neuer perceived of thoſe that owe them. Againe, to anſwer their pittifull hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor that they would not have Bees killed: Hath not God given all creatures unto us for our benefit, and to be uſed accordingly as may ſeeme good unto us for our good? we ſee that many other creatures of greater ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt are daily killed in infinite numbers for our ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and often for our pleaſure, and is it not lawfull for vs, to uſe theſe ſilly creatures in ſuch ſort as they may be moſt for our benefit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which I take to be the right uſe of them and the very end of their creation?</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:159996:32"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>Yes without all queſtion, for mine owne part I make no doubt to uſe them ſo, if it bee moſt for our profit, and alſo for the good of the reſt, as you have to my underſtanding ſufficiently proved, and therefore I ſuppoſe you uſe that way altogether and never drive any untill about September.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>Yes that I doe ſometimes, and that to my benefit. But it is onely in this caſe: when I have a Hive that ſtandeth two or three yeeres and doth not ſwarme (as amongſt many Hives there will almoſt ever be ſome ſuch) which I take to be upon ſome diſlike, or fault in the hiue, or Combes, or elſe in the over bigneſſe thereof. About the beginning of <hi>Iuly</hi> I doe many times driue ſuch a hiue, yea perhaps two or three in a yeere, and haue had very good ſucceſſe after it. For whereas they have ſtood before, and have not ſwarmed at all, I haue had two ſwarmes of a hive, the next yeere follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. But often and for the moſt part they haue proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red much better than before, and haue yeelded mee ſome good increaſe. And I hold it very probable and likely ſeldome to faile that a hiue may be driven about the fift or ſixt of <hi>Iuly,</hi> ſo that it hath not ſwarmed that yeere, and may doe very well. But let it caſt but one ſwarme, and then driue it although it be a weeke ſooner, and I dare hold three to one that it will periſh the winter following, except the yeere be very good. For when a hiue ſwarmeth, the moſt part of the Bees goe away in the ſwarme, as you may perceiue, for ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times you ſhall haue a ſwarme ſo great, that it will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt fill a hiue as bigge as that it came out of, and yet haue no Combes in it at all: marry true it is, that they leaue much ſpat and young Bees behind them, which will preſently after be come to perfection and ready to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:159996:32"/>labour. But if you driue your hiue ſhortly after, you deſtroy them all, and ſo utterly diſcourage and ſpoyle all the reſt of your Bees in that hiue for euer, or elſe it is a great chance.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>Surely Sir, I like very well your dryving of hiues in manner as you teach; for ſuch as haue many, as you and ſome others that I know: yet for a young beginner that hath but a few, to doe ſo, it would be long ere he ſhould increaſe his ſtore, when he muſt kill ſome of them he hath.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>If it hole profitable for the increaſe of Bees, in many, it holdeth good alſo where there are few. For I will propound the caſe as if I had but one hive. Now I do know whether it bee an old ſtock, or a ſwarme of the laſt yeere: if it be an old ſtocke, and I feare it will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay with age, rather than yeele increaſe. I will drive it betimes, as I taught in the laſt ſection, into another hiue, and not looke for a ſwarme no longer than the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of <hi>Iuly.</hi> And then have I a ſtock as good as a ſwarm, whereof I may expect ſwarmes three or foure yeeres after, without neede to driue it againe: But if my ſtocke be young and caſt me a ſwarme, I will not drive it that yeere, untill my ſtore be increaſed: the next yeere if ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther one or both my hiues doe ſwarme, I may haue one at the leaſt to driue and yet my ſtocke will goe forwards notwithſtanding: and thus haue I many or few, it will be the beſt courſe for me both to preſerue my ſtocke and to take ſome honey alſo, for there will be more honey in one hiue at Bartholomew-tide, then in foure at mid-ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer or in the beginning of <hi>Iuly.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>Your reaſon is good, but a little more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the driving of hives at Midſomer, or about that time. Although it be granted, (as I confeſſe it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:159996:33"/>by that you have ſaid) that Bees driuen at that time of the yeere, are in apparant danger of death them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, yet can I not perceive how they ſhould procure the hurt or deſtruction of any others, becauſe the other in likelihood ſhould bee ſtronger than they, and their hives better filled than theirs, and ſo ſhould bee able to make reſiſtance. Againe, why ſhould not late ſwarms who are alſo poore enough, of which you ſave ſome, hurt their neighbours as well as the drifts?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>You muſt underſtand, that although other Bees will indeed to their power reſiſt robbers, yet at one time or other, partly by ſtealth, and partly by force, they will get into their hives, and rob them, and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in the winter time, for then other Bees ſleep: but the poore ones being pinched with hunger, will in a warm day ſeek abroad into other hives, and yet the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Bees will at that time ſcant perceive them, as you may ſee that Mice, Spiders, Mothes, wormes, or any ſuch like will eaſily get into hives in the winter, if there be any roome left for them to get in, which in the ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer dare not come neere, becauſe the Bees will then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt and ſting them, being in the prime of their ſtrength. Now why ſwarmes be not robbers as well as drifts, the reaſon is manifeſt: For they are compoſed for the moſt part of yong Bees, who know not how to ſhift and rob as the old ones do, and having not been robbed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſeek not to rob others.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>In what manner do you make your choice of thoſe ſtocks that you meane to drive at Bartholo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mewtide?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>For the moſt part of the eldeſt hives. Becauſe in time Bees will decay and die of themſelues, although they were neuer driuen; for that their combes will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:159996:33"/>black and unſauory, ſo that they will miſlike them: and againe, old Bees are not ſo good for increaſe and breeding as the young, nor yet (as ſome hold) ſo ſtrong or luſty for labour, and therefore as I ſaid, I alwayes, or for the moſt part, driue of my eldeſt hiues, ever ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing this, that they haue caſt me one ſwarm at the leaſt, that yeere.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>It ſeemeth to me, that a hiue which hath not ſwarmed, ſhould gather more hony than one that hath ſwarmed, becauſe in likelihood there ſhould bee more Bees, and many hands, as they ſay, make light work, and fill the hive the better?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>It is out of all queſtion, that hive which hath not ſwarmed, will haue more ſtore of hony than a hive that hath ſwarmed that yeere, yea and often times a ſwarm more than a ſtock. But a man that deſireth to haue both profit and increaſe, muſt ſo vſe the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that he may haue profit for the preſent in ſuch ſort as he may continue, and ſtill maintain and (if may be) increaſe his ſtock for the time to come: for if my ſtock haue ſwarmed, I do not diminiſh my ſtore, though I driue my ſtock, whereas if I driue it before it hath ſwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, I muſt driue it early, and ſo haue little or no ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, or elſe if I driue it late, loſe ſtock and all, and ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh my ſtore. And yet I am not ſo earneſt of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, but that ſometime, when I haue good ſtore, and my Bees ſwarm well, I do driue one that I perceiue to be of an extraordinary waight, though it hath not ſwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med at all: Marry I do not uſe it often, neither would I do it at all, except I had good plenty of hiues, as you ſee, for I utterly miſlike it in a new beginner.</p>
               <p>Again, another reaſon why I take ſuch as haue ſwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med is, for that ſometimes (eſpecially in wet ſummers)
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:159996:34"/>ſome hiues will ſwarm ſo much, as there will not be Bees enough to keep the hony warm in the winter time, nor in any ſort to furniſh the hive; ſo that they would be in danger to die, although they ſhould not be driuen, and eſpecially if they be of any great age.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>How long do you think the Bees in a hive will continue and live, if they ſhould not bee driven at all, but to let them alone as long as they live?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>How long the Bees in a hive will continue and live, I hold a very vncertaine thing to affirme; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I know that many haue ſet down their opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons concerning the ſame, with great variety and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of judgement, which I liſt not to ſtand about to confute, nor do I think it neceſſary. Only this I ſay, that no man can judge by the time a Bee will liue, (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the time were certainly known, which I think no man can iuſtly determine) how long a hive will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue with Bees in it; becauſe all experience doth teach that Bees are every yeere daily renewed in the ſummer time: and yet this is the rule they pretend to go by. But <hi>I</hi> think rather that this thing muſt bee known, by the time that Bees will like and proſper in a hive a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt their old combes, which with continuance will (as <hi>I</hi> ſayd before) become black and unſavory; and that will bee ſooner or later, as the Bees ſtand to health, and the yeeres happen to proue good or euill for them. And therefore <hi>I</hi> would aduiſe no man to make triall of this matter, except hee like better of curioſity than pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit. My ſelfe do not ordinarily ſuffer any to ſtand above three, foure, or fiue yeares at the moſt, for if <hi>I</hi> ſee a hive like well, and that doth caſt me a ſwarm euery yeere, <hi>I</hi> let it ſtand the longer; whereas otherwiſe <hi>I</hi> driue it the ſooner, eſpecially if it caſt mee no ſwarm in the two firſt
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:159996:34"/>yeeres: But then I onely change it into another hiue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the beginning of <hi>Iuly,</hi> and ſaue the Bees to ſee if they will doe better in another hiue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Googe</hi> doth keepe a great adoe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the gelding of Bees (as he calleth it) and the proportion that he thinketh fit to leaue in the hiues for the Bees. And <hi>I</hi> conceiue his meaning to be, to take from every hiue ſome part, and to leaue them ſufficient to keepe them in the winter, and ſo by this meanes doth not altogether driue or kill any at all. If it will performe that, it ſeemeth to me to be a very good way; yet doe <hi>I</hi> not remember that ever <hi>I</hi> haue hard it ſo much as ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of in this Country: what doe you thinke of it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>Marry Sir, <hi>I</hi> thinke it a very good way for thoſe that are willing to be rid of their Bees: For let any man that hath beene accuſtomed amongſt Bees conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, how this thing can be done, without great trouble, hurt, or danger to the Bees, and alſo much loſſe of their honey. And therefore <hi>I</hi> neuer knew any ſo abſurd to practiſe that way that ever <hi>I</hi> could heare of, for which cauſe <hi>I</hi> will not trouble my ſelfe to confute it, as palpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble enough to all men of any underſtanding or know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>In what manner doe you uſe your Bees when you drive them, doe you burne them or drowne them? For <hi>I</hi> haue heard of ſome that uſe the one way, and ſome the other, but whether is beſt <hi>I</hi> know not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> make no great difference betweene the one way or the other, whether is the better. But my manner of driving my hiues and killing of my Bees is in this ſort. When <hi>I</hi> purpoſe to driue any hiue, <hi>I</hi> take an empty hive and ſticke it, like as <hi>I</hi> haue taught to put in aſwarme, and then with a ſheete put about it and the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:159996:35"/>hiue, <hi>I</hi> purpoſe to driue, uſing it as the common manner is in driving of hives.</p>
               <p>The order and manner whereof is ſo well knowne al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt to every man, that I ſhall not need (as I thinke) to make any further ſpeech thereof. But when I haue dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the Bees as cleane as I can out of the Hiue where they were, into the empty one, I ſet up the ſame in the place where the other hive ſtood, untill it be good and late in the night, and that I have taken the honey out of the hive that I haue driven, by which time the Bees will all be gone cloſe up together into the top of the hiue. Then I take it from the place againe gently, and carry it to ſome plaine place made of purpoſe, and with my hand ſtampe the hiue hard upon the place, and ſo all the Bees will fall out: Then have I ready a broad board, which I preſently lay upon them, and tread upon it, and ſo preſently kill them all, that none eſcape, whereas, in the burning or drowning of them or any other way that ever I could ſee, many get away and trouble the reſt of the Bees.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>I thinke it is not good to drive any hiues untill night, becauſe of troubling the Bees, and to auoyd the danger of ſtinging, which muſt needs happen in the day time.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>For mine owne part I ſeldome or never driue any untill ſomewhat late in the euening. Yet I haue ſeene ſome drive hives at noone day, and when it is rainy, it may reaſonably well bee done, yet as I ſaid, I doe hold the euening beſt and leaſt troubleſome. And when I drive three or foure in a night (as ſometimes I doe) it is but ſitting up ſo much the longer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>When you driue ſuch hiues as are hoyſted, and raiſed up with Bricke-bats or ſuch other things:
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:159996:35"/>which of neceſſity you muſt take away, when you driue them: how doe you make the hives agree and fit well together that the Bees may goe well out of the one hiue into the other: becauſe the Combes will be longer than the lower part of the hiue, and therefore it cannot come neere or goe cloſe to the other hiue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>For the avoiding of that inconvenience, which will be troubleſome I confeſſe, you muſt do thus, Let your hive into which you will driue your Bees, be ſomewhat broader than the Hive you drive, and then, the ends of the Combes will goe into it, and you ſhall driue the Bees into it without any trouble or inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience at all, more than if the hiue were not hoyſted at all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>After what manner doe you order your honey, for if I be not deceived, I haue ſeene much better hony in ſome places, than in other ſome: But whether the cauſe hath beene in the uſing of it, in the difference of the place where it was gathered, or in the goodneſſe or badneſſe of the yeere wherein it was gathered, that I was not able to determine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>Without all doubt, any of theſe three cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes may worke ſome effect in the goodneſſe of honey. Yet doe <hi>I</hi> hold the well ordering of it, to be a great and principall cauſe to have good honey, for it may bee ſpoyled at the firſt taking of it out of the Hiue, or after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in the euill keeping thereof. You ſee what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of honey that is, which we call Weſterne honey, which for mine owne part <hi>I</hi> loath to taſte, and <hi>I</hi> haue ſeene ſome hereabouts not much better. But how they uſe it I know not, nor haue any liſt to underſtand. But howſoeuer it might not be of the beſt gathering, yet <hi>I</hi> verily beleeue it would have beene much better, if it had
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:159996:36"/>beene well handled. Concerning the manner that I uſe and like, <hi>I</hi> will ſhew you two wayes. The firſt way is this, Take a great earthen panne or ſuch like, and ſpread over it a large new Canvas cloath, that is very thinne: and wring the honey out of the Combes, as hard as you can, when you haue done all, knit the cloath at the foure corners together, and hang it up by putting a ſticke or ſtaffe through at the knitting, right ouer the ſaid panne, and ſo let it runne into the panne of its own accord with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out forcing. Then put it up into a pot that hath not beene waſhed, or if it be waſhed, let it be perfectly dry againe, and ſo keepe it for vſe, and you muſt take heed that no water or other things runne neere unto it, to fall into it. For there be many things that will corrupt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. The other way is in this ſort, in ſtead of your cloath take a ſearce and lay it over your panne, and ſo to refine your honey by letting it runne through it. Both which wayes <hi>I</hi> take to be good enough. And this is all that I uſe to doe with my honey at the driving of my hiues. And as for the keeping of it afterwards, it ſhall need nothing elſe, but that the pots be cloſe and ſafe from any thing comming or falling into them. And if any roſſe worketh or ſpurgeth up (as ſometimes it will doe) you muſt take it away. Yet this <hi>I</hi> muſt tell you, that the honey of aſwarme will not be ſo thicke as that of an old ſtocke, nor honey that is gathered late, ſo good as that which is gathered in the former part of the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer: But <hi>I</hi> ſuppoſe the chiefe reaſon to be, for that the former hath continued longer amongſt the Bees, who with their heate haue compoſed it to a better ſubſtance, then that which hath lyen a leſſer while amongſt them, and therefore is not ſo well refined as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:159996:36"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>After what manner doe you deale with your Combes to try out the waxe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>The manner thereof is ſo common and well knowne to every one, as <hi>I</hi> ſhall not need (but for forme ſake) to ſay any thing thereof. And therefore <hi>I</hi> will be the more briefe. When the honey is all gotten out, put all your Combes (as well thoſe that had no honey in them as the reſt) into a good quantity of faire water, (of this water ſome make a kind of drink called Meath) which if you doe change your Combes into other wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and boyle them a little while, till the Combes are well melted, then put the Combes and water together into a Canvas bagge, made like an Ipocras bagge, viz. narrow at the lower end, and ſtraine as much as you can thorow the ſame, letting it runne into a veſſell of cold water, caſting away the roſſe that remaineth in the bag. After this, gather the wax well together and melt it in a poſnet or ſuch like at a ſoft fire, and let it be made into what forme you pleaſe, but if it be not purified at the firſt trying well enough (as peradventure it will not be) then try or melt it againe, firſt having ſcraped or pared of the roſſe that ſettleth at the bottome. But if you will haue your waxe very yellow, you muſt not put to it the Combes, of your ſwarmes that you drive, but try that by it ſelfe, for the waxe of ſwarmes is much whiter then the waxe of an old ſtocke; and being tryed with it, will make it haue a more pale colour then otherwiſe it would haue. And this is as much as (in my conceit) ſhall be needfull to be done concerning the well keeping and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of Bees.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Googe</hi> and others that haue written of the ordering of Bees, make report of many ſorts of Trees, Herbes and Plants, which as they ſay are profitable and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:159996:37"/>helping to Bees, if they bee placed and ſet neere unto them, and that by gathering of them, they will proſper and increaſe much the better. Therefore I pray you let me not be without your opinion, and iudgement con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning that point alſo. And if you think them any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance to their proſperity, that you would ſet down the names of thoſe that you think moſt neceſſary, and the manner how and when to plant them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>It cannot be denied, that as all other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are benefited and furthered by ſuch things as Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath created for their ſuſtenance and delight, euen ſo the ſilly Bees alſo are not without their benefit by being neere ſuch trees and plants as they ioy and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to gather of, eſpecially ſuch as bloſſom in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the Spring, when few or no plants are to bee found for that purpoſe growing in the fields: but if Aprill be once paſt, I hold it not much materiall, becauſe then euery field hath plenty of flowers and plants for them to gather of. And therefore I do like well that you ſhould plant ſuch things about your gardens and yards, the names whereof and the manner how to do it, <hi>I</hi> will declare unto you, of ſo many as <hi>I</hi> can remember. But for thoſe that bloſſom later, as things of leſſe regard for this purpoſe, <hi>I</hi> will only name them without any more ado. And yet one thing <hi>I</hi> will here remember vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, that ſhould haue been ſpoken of before; <hi>I</hi> hold it very good to plant yong trees about and neere unto your Bees (ſo that they ſtand not to the South of them) which will be both good for them to light and ſettle up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in ſwarming time, as alſo for them to gather vpon their bloſſoms if they be fruit trees.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>What fruit trees do you hold beſt for that purpoſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:159996:37"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>Such as bloſſom early, as Cherrytrees, Plumtrees, and Pearetrees; and in that number you may alſo reckon Apricocks and Peaches, which bloſſom at that time of the yeere, or rather more early: for if you obſerue it, you ſhall ſee the Bees exceedingly to gather in their bloſſoms, when they blow.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>What ſorts of them do you think beſt to be planted, for I would plant of ſuch as ſhould bee beſt for them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>It is not my purpoſe in this place to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh of the goodneſſe of fruits, as not materiall to the matter in hand; becauſe Bees delight as well in the bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoms of the worſt as of the beſt. And again, I ſuppoſe it a buſle peece of work to performe, for euery mans taſte will challenge a cenſure in that thing, becauſe we ſee one man loueth that which another can ſcarce abide to ſee: yet would I wiſh you if you plant, to plant ſuch as are of moſt account, and that you ſhall beſt fancy in your taſte. Now concerning the manner how to plant them, it muſt be done in the winter time: and if your ſoyle of ground be light, as of ſand, or ſuch like, then plant them between October and December, ſetting them ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what deep into the ground; but if it bee a heauy ſoyle, and the bottom be of clay, then ſet them fleet and ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low into the ground, and remoue them not untill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween December and February, for the coldneſſe and wetneſſe of that kinde of ground will do them much hurt if they be ſoon remoued.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>Are not Appletrees alſo good for them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, without all queſtion, they are moſt excellently good for them to ſettle and light vpon, and the Bees will alſo gather of their flowers or bloſſoms: but becauſe they blow later, I do not account them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:159996:38"/>thoſe that are altogether ſo good as the other for Bees to gather upon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>At what time of the yeere are they to bee planted?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>At all one time with the other trees before named, and the ſame manner <hi>I</hi> would wiſh you to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue in the planting or ſetting of them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>What kinde of ſoyle do Apple trees like beſt?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> hold that Appletrees do beſt delight and proſper in a ſoyle mixed of clay and ſand; For ſandy grounds will make them much ſubject to the canker, and claiy grounds as much to bee anonyed with moſſe, and therefore it is out of all doubt, that a ſoyle compoſed of them both, is moſt fit to plant them in. But herein <hi>I</hi> would not haue you take me to mean ſuch a mixed ſoyle as many yards and gardens are, which with continuall dunging grow to be a black earth, for in ſuch grounds Appletrees are moſt of all ſubject to the canker; but <hi>I</hi> meane it of ſuch as naturally or by art haue ſuch a mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, without any dung.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>Do you hold dung to be hurtfull to trees?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>Yea verily, and this is a generall rule, that for the moſt part of plants and herbs dung is very good and profitable, but for trees <hi>I</hi> hold it rather hurtfull than good?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>Now you haue ſpoken of trees that you hold beſt to be planted for the benefit of Bees, <hi>I</hi> pray you do the ſame alſo for herbs and plants.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>In the firſt place for plants that bloſſom early, <hi>I</hi> will remember Roſemary, which flowreth both in the Spring and againe in Autumne, in the flowers whereof Bees do exceedingly delight: it is planted of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:159996:38"/>the ſlip, and almoſt at any time of the yeere, eſpecially in the Spring; it proſpereth beſt in a light ſoyle, and is to bee planted on the South or Weſt ſide of a wall or pale, for it loueth warmth, as a plant that groweth na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally beſt in hot countreys.</p>
               <p>Borage alſo is a plant in the flowers whereof Bees do very much delight to gather, and it bloſſometh moſt part of the yeere; it is planted beſt of the ſeed, at any time of the yeere, and loueth a fat ſoyle.</p>
               <p>In this number I will alſo place the Raſpis or Iram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boys, although that they flower ſomewhat later than the other, for it is exceeding that Bees will lie and gather in them: they are planted of the yong ſhoots from the roots, in February and March, and ioy in any kinde of ground almoſt, ſo it be any thing good.</p>
               <p>There is alſo a little plant called Pulſatilla that flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in the beginning of Aprill, that they alſo much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in: it is planted of the ſeed, in the winter time, and loueth ſomewhat a faſt and ſtiffe ſoyle.</p>
               <p>Rapes, Turnips, and Cabbages, are plants that Bees delight to gather in their flowers, but they flower in the ſecond yeere after their planting, they grow of ſeed, and delight in a fat mid well dunged ſoyle.</p>
               <p>Bearfoot is alſo a plant that flowreth early, and Bees do much delight to gather of the bloſſomes thereof; it is planted of the ſeed or yong ſets in the Spring, it loueth a good and fat ſoyle, yet is apt enough to grow any where.</p>
               <p>Beanes are alſo plants that Bees do much delight to gather in their flowers, who if they bee planted early, will blow in March and Aprill, and ſo be very good for Bees that are neere unto them; the manner of planting of them is ſo commonly known, as I need ſay nothing thereof.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:159996:39"/>
               <p>Sundry other ſmall plants there are that flower early, which Bees will gather of, as Primroſes, ſingle Violets, and ſuch like, the recitall whereof would bee to ſmall purpoſe, becauſe thoſe moſt materiall and fitteſt to bee planted, are aforenamed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>Then you are of opinion, that theſe plants and trees, or the moſt part of them, you would aduiſe ſuch as keep Bees, to plant about them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>I do indeed, for as I haue elſewhere ſayd, in the Spring of the yeere when Bees are weak, and lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or nothing to bee found in the fields, a very ſmall thing maintaineth life, and cheriſheth them, as mine owne experience hath taught me. For by reaſon that <hi>I</hi> haue ſome plenty of ſuch trees and plants, I haue ſeen my Bees luſty and ſtrong in the Spring, when others haue been feeble and weak, yea and haue wrought and laboured well, when others haue found little or nothing abroad to do them any good.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>You ſpeak as though there were many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther plants that bloſſom more late in the yeere, which Bees alſo do gather of, <hi>I</hi> pray you which be they?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>If May bee once well entred, the fields al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt euery where yeeld abundance of flowers, both for the profit and delight of all creatures, as eſpecially for the benefit of Bees, a catalogue of the moſt part of thoſe that they vſually gather of, I will briefly ſet down; not for that I hold it neceſſary to plant them in gardens, or other places, for the benefit of your Bees, (except ſuch as ſerue for other good and neceſſary vſes) for that were an endleſſe work, but only to acquaint you with their names, and to ſatisfie in part the minds of ſome curious readers.</p>
               <p>I will begin with the Sallow tree, which beareth the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:159996:39"/>Palme, vpon which Bees will gather exceeding much, and it might haue been placed among the for moſt num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, for the timely Bloſſoming, and the profit that Bees take by it, but that it is of that ſort which is not conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient to be planted neere a houſe, nor in a garden or or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard, becauſe it beareth no fruit, nor hath in it any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectation or pleaſure for any extraordinary uſe or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light.</p>
               <p>The Maple alſo is a tree that Bees much delight to gather in the flowers thereof, and they alſo come ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what early.</p>
               <p>The Birch and Beech trees are alſo good for Bees to gather in the time of their flowring, as alſo the plants following:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Angelica, Melilot, Stecados, Avens, Solidago, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>razanica, Virga aurea, Liſimachia, Radix cava, Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, Balme, Clover,</hi> eſpecially that with the white flower. <hi>Bramble</hi> or <hi>Blackberry buſh;</hi> in the time of the flowring of this plant hapneth the greateſt plenty of hony. <hi>Thyme, Branck</hi> or <hi>Buck Hiſop, Lavender, Sage.</hi> And theſe are the principall that I can now call to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>Are there not ſome trees and plants that are hurtfull vnto Bees, and ſo not good to bee placed neere them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, ſundry, whereof the cheifeſt are theſe that follow: the Yew tree, the Box tree.</p>
               <p>And of plants theſe, Spurge, Wormwood, Woad, wilde Cucumers, Mayweed: ſome hold the Elme in flowring time to be hurtfull for Bees.</p>
               <p>Any oylie or vnctious matter is very hurtfull for Bees.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, I am bold to claime your promiſe, for your fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:159996:40"/>declaration vnto me of the nature, breeding and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of Bees.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, I will declare unto you my opinion and conceit concerning your requeſt. And yet I muſt heere tell you, that as in our former ſpeech I did chiefly truſt to mine owne experience and practice amongſt Bees; in this dayes worke I muſt as much leane to, and be ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the opinions of others: now and then mixing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them ſome of mine owne obſervations and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments, yet ſo, as I rather leave them to the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of thoſe of better iudgement, then affirming them as a certaine and undoubted truth. Becauſe many of the queſtions that will offer themſelues here to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered of, are ſo intricate and doubtfull, that they ſhall neede much obſervation and great iudgement to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine. But to proceede, <hi>Ariſtotle, Virgil,</hi> and divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that have curiouſly ſearched and written, of the nature, gouernment, and breeding of Bees: doe make many ſorts and kinds of Bees, as well for their difference in their quantity and bigneſſe, as alſo in their faſhion and forme. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> he liketh beſt the ſhort, ſpeckled, and well knit Bee, and <hi>Virgil</hi> preferreth the long, ſmoth, and faire Bee. But for mine owne part, as one not ſo well acquainted with the variety of their kinds (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I could never perceive in our countrey any great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference) I doe like beſt ſuch Bees as be gentle and well coloured, for the waſpiſh and fell Bees are never good, neither for increaſe or profit, and the evill coloured are not in health.</p>
               <p>But becauſe every man muſt content himſelfe with ſuch as he hath, or can get, it behoveth thoſe that haue of the worſt ſort, ſo to uſe them by gentle and good meanes, that their curſt and waſpiſh qualities, may bee
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:159996:40"/>bettered and made more gentle.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pliny</hi>ſaith that the Bee is the onely beſt of all Inſects whatſoeuer, exceeding every one in profit, excellence and uſe, they are creatures of a ſtrange compoſition and much ſtranger ſubſtance, for they have neither fleſh, blood, bones, or ſinewes, doe not moue by ioynts, haue neither chyne, nor griſtle; fat or excrement; but are compact and made of a corporeall ſubſtance or middle nature betweene all theſe, through which the life or mouing is diſperſed generally and not ſeated or ſettled in any particular part; as other creatures haue in the heart and in the braine, whence it commeth (as we ſee by daily experience,) that if you devide and cut them or diſmember them into two parts, each part will equally liue a long time after ſuch diſmembrings.</p>
               <p>They haue no Intraylls or other inward Organs, by which either to retaine or evacuat, onely a certaine Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duite or pipe, which inſtead of a gut (being wrapped together carrieth and diſpoſeth whatſoeuer it recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth.</p>
               <p>They haue many feete, that is to ſay, ſixe, and the reaſon thereof is, becauſe (as before I ſaid) the vitall parts are not ſeated in any one member, but diſperſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad and communicated to every other part of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, holding the leaſt of it reſidence in the head.</p>
               <p>They haue wings to tranſport and carry them to what place they pleaſe, and alſo to bring them home when they are laden with the wealth and riches of their labours.</p>
               <p>Their feete are crooked, and longer from the bent downeward then from the bent to the body, and the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger the feet are, the better: for it is a great ſigne of long life and faithfull labour.</p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:159996:41"/>
               <p>They haue all the fiue ſenſes which man hath, and in a liberall proportion: As firſt eyes, by which they ſee and diſcerne to diſtinguiſh of one Flower from another, and to make choice of that which is moſt amiable and beſt agreeing to their natures and profits.</p>
               <p>Then hearing, by which they liſten unto ſounds, as the commands of their Soveraigne or Maſter Bee, the noyſe of their companions and their one or others Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, as we ſee by daily experience, when the tinkling of a Baſon or ſuch like Inſtrument will congregate and gather them together, when the ſwarmes are never ſo farre or wide diſperſed.</p>
               <p>Then ſmelling, by which they know the ſweet Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers from the bitter hearbs, cleaving unto Roſes, Violets, Bugloſſe, Borrage and the like, but eſchewing and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoning Onions, Garlicke, Rew, and Hemlocke, nay ſo excellently curious are they in their ſmelling that they will not abide any diſtaſtefull ſmell that is about them that Gouerne them, and will naturally take an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence at a ſtinking breath.</p>
               <p>Then feeling, as is moſt eaſily to be perceiued by their embracing and loue to the things they affect, and the offence and reuenge they take, when at any time they are oppreſt or offended, being ſo ſenſible of paine that they will loſe their ſting (which is halfe a loſſe of life) rather than to bee tormented, or pained above their nature.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, they haue the ſenſe of taſting, being able to iudge which Flower is ſweete and will affoord plenty of Honey, and which is gummy or ſlymie from whence they may draw waxe.</p>
               <p>The Bee (of all creatures) is the moſt laborious, and neuer giveth over his dayes labour from the midſt of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:159996:41"/>
                  <hi>Aprill</hi> till the beginning of <hi>November,</hi> neither would he then ceaſe, were it not for his two mortall enemies, Snow and Froſts, the bitterneſſe of both which he can neither indure nor ſuffer. And thus much I thought good to ſay concerning their nature or kinds.</p>
               <p>Now concerning their breeding, there is much adoe, and great variety amongſt writers, as well for the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of their breeding, as alſo for the time of their bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth, and the comming to perfection of their brood. Some hold the Drone to be the Male, and the Bee the female, and that they ingender by copulation. Others affirme that they ingender not, but that they gather their young ones, upon ſome Flowers: againe ſome are of opinion that the Kings or Maſter Bees, doe ingender all the reſt: and ſome that they lay egges and ſit upon them, which will come to be Bees in 45 dayes. But I am of opinion with Mr. <hi>Southerne,</hi> that they doe blow as a Flye and Waſpe doth in their holes or Cells, and as the blowes of the Flyes are nouriſhed by the fleſh wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they are blowne, and the young of the Waſpes by the earth wherein they are bred, ſo the ſpat or brood of the Bees are nouriſhed by honey and water: For in the Combes wherein they are bred, you ſhall ſee every ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond or third hole or cell filled with water or honey, whereof if they want, their ſpat will periſh. And if they are bred by copulation (as ſome affirme, and as may be, without contradiction to the former opinion) being thereby made able to ſpat or caſt their brood, I could like of their opinions which hold the Drones to be the Males. Becauſe ail experience doth teach that never any Bees were, or can be without Drones; and therefore without all doubt nature hath created them for ſome principall uſe: and I nor no man can perceive any
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:159996:42"/>greater then this, or as almoſt fit for little or nothing elſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>If that were ſo, I me thinke there ſhould then be as many Drones as Bees, and againe the Bees would not kill them, becauſe we doe not read of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther creature, that the Males are killed by the Females.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>You muſt not thinke that I would certaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affirme that, which ſo many learned men have but geſſed at, yet by way of reaſoning I may thus much ſay in anſwer of your obiection: We ſee that many crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures doe increase beſt, when there are but a few Males amongſt them, in compariſon of the Females, as Kyne, Sheepe, Coneyes, and many others; and although the Females of theſe kinds cannot, of will not, kill their Males themſelues, yet who knoweth whether this be not a peculiar property in the Bees or no, when they find themſelues to be ſurcharged with them. And this is moſt certaine, that the Bees never fall to killing of their Drones untill breeding time be almoſt out for that yeere.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>How long is it ere the ſpat or brood of the Bees will come to perfection, and be ready to gather?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>Moſt of the ancient writers doe hold, that from the firſt calling of their ſpat to the comming forth of the ſame, it is forty and fiue dayes. But Mr. <hi>Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne</hi> affirmeth, that they bring forth their brood in fifteen dayes at the moſt. Yet notwithſtanding Mr. <hi>Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thernes</hi> ſuppoſed reaſons to the contrary, I rather yeeld to the former opinion, as moſt probable by farre in my conceit</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>I pray you what are his reaſons that he aleadgeth againſt ſo many great and ancient learned men?</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:159996:42"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>He alleadgeth two, but the former of them he anſwereth himſelfe, namely, that an old ſtocke after it hath caſt a ſwarme within nine dayes hath caſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but (this faieth he) may be alleadged to be of the remnant of the other, or elſe ſome that then were almoſt ready to flye, and I ſay that this allegation is true: (or I have of ten ſeene a hive caſt a ſwarme, and within foure dayes caſt another.</p>
               <p>His other reaſon is, that he hath had a ſwarme put into a new hive, which hath ſwarmed againe within fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene dayes after, and therefore hee concludeth that theſe muſt needs be bred ſince their putting into that hive.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>His firſt reaſon I confeſſe it is but weake, but, how doe you anſwer this laſt?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>For anſwer of the other, I ſaid that no grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter proofe then he alleadgeth, cannot (in my conceit) weigh downe, the long obſervations and reputations of ſo many learned men, concurring in one opinion, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of no doubt ſome of them might and did make tryall. But to let them paſſe, I hold that a great ſwarme (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving laboured 15 dayes, in which time about the begin<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of <hi>Iuly,</hi> they might almoſt fill the hive with waxe and ſome honey, and alſo haue left good ſtore behind them of ſpat) may ſwarme out more then halfe the Bees, which will be a pretty ſwarme, and yet leaue ſome ſtore behind in the hive to maintaine their ſpat, and alſo to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour untill the other be ready: as my ſelfe haue ſeene the like. Nevertheleſſe when ſuch a thing happeneth, it is as I thinke upon ſome fault in the hive, or other diſlike, and will put the ſame in danger to dye the next winter as himſelfe confeſſeth, which could not be, if all the old ſtore remain'd behind, who were able wel to maintain the hive.</p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:159996:43"/>
               <p>But in very truth, whoſoeuer ſhall obſerue the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of their breeding, muſt needs confeſſe, that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bring forth in fifteen dayes, nor neere unto it, as Mr. <hi>Southern</hi> conceiteth; for when Bees firſt caſt their ſpat, it is as ſmall almoſt as a little fly-blow, then it encreaſeth to the faſhion of a worme, and will be quick, and dieth again, laſtly it obtaineth the form of a Bee ſome good time before it come to perfection, whoſe continuance is ſo much, that by mine owne experience I dare affirme, that Mr. <hi>Southern</hi> is miſtaken in this matter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>Although this ſhould be granted that you ſay, yet how ſhould they do for another maſter Bee to go out with the ſwarme, or elſe to remaine behind in the hive?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>I do not take it for certain, that there is but one maſter Bee to a hive, or ſwarme, for ſome hold there are to euery one two, and ſome more, and yet peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the multitude of maſter Bees in that ſwarme, may be one principall cauſe to make it ſwarme againe; for it is an extraordinary matter to haue a ſwarm caſt a ſwarm againe, eſpecially ſo ſoone as Mr. <hi>Southern</hi> ſpeaketh of, namely within fifteen dayes; yet I confeſſe, I haue ſeene the like by a great and forward ſwarm, or when two haue gone together of their own accord, betimes in the yeere.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>But how do you know that the ſwarm that it caſt was not of a new increaſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>Beſides the reaſons that I haue alleaged, this alſo may bee added, for that in the like caſe a man ſhall perceiue but a few Bees to be left behinde, for they will work much more ſlowly vntill the time come to bring forth their brood, and then they will bee full a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, as before, which would not be perceiued if the old
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:159996:43"/>Bees had been all left behinde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>What part of the yeere do you take to bee the principall time of their breeding?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>They will breed or ſpat from Aprill vntill it be mid September; but the principall time I take to be between mid Aprill and mid Iuly; for between thoſe times, if you driue any hiue, you ſhall euer finde great ſtore of ſpat and yong Bees: and yet aſwarm will breed very much, euen vntill the end of Auguſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>Here commeth to my remembrance a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, which I purpoſed ere this to haue propounded vnto you: I beleeue you haue heard it to go for a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon receiued opinion, that Bees after they haue loſt their ſting by ſtinging of any thing, will bee Drones, which Mr. <hi>Southern</hi> ſeemeth to ſcoffe at, I pray you, what think you concerning that matter?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>I am fully of Mr. <hi>Southerns</hi> opinion for that, becauſe what Bee ſoeuer hath loſt her ſting, ſhall loſe her life alſo within a ſhort time after, as loſing ſome part of her intrals withall, for Drones are bred as other Bees are, as any man that driueth a hive, ſhall well know the Drone ſpat by the bigneſſe thereof, before it come to any perfection.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>Well Sir, now I pray you, let mee haue your opinion concerning the King, or maſter Bee, firſt for his quanity and form, for their number, and laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for their power and command ouer the reſt of the Bees?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> and <hi>Virgil</hi> do make mention of two ſorts of Kings or maſter Bees, the one ſort being of a golden colour, very fayre and gallant to the ſight; and theſe they ſuppoſe to be the beſt: but the other ſort are of the colour of other Bees. Now all the maſter Bees
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:159996:44"/>that euer I ſaw, differ little in colour from the other Bees, but that their legs are yellow, inclining to a golden co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour: they are bigger than another Bee, and much more longer, almoſt by the one halfe.</p>
               <p>Concerning the number of them in a hive, I dare not determine any thing for certaine; yet do I think that one hath the principall command, if they agree and proſper well: their yong ones or ſpat are bred in their owne houſes or cels, and not amongſt the other Bees, as I haue often ſeene.</p>
               <p>Now for their authority and command, with the great obedience which the other yeeld unto them, I will cite the opinion of <hi>Virgil,</hi> Engliſhed by Mr. <hi>Geoge.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Not <hi>Egypt</hi> in his prime,</l>
                  <l>Nor <hi>Lydia</hi> large and wide,</l>
                  <l>Nor yet the <hi>Parthian</hi> people great,</l>
                  <l>Nor all the <hi>Medes</hi> beſide,</l>
                  <l>Do ſo their King obey,</l>
                  <l>Who being ſafe and well,</l>
                  <l>Their minds are altogether one,</l>
                  <l>He only heares the bell.</l>
               </q>
               <p>If the King periſh, the reſt of the Bees neuer proſper, but come to nought. Not long ſince I had two ſwarmes did ariſe almoſt at one time, and when the firſt was almoſt hived, the other came to them, and when part were gone into one hive, I tooke that away cleane, and put another hive in the place, into which the moſt part of my Bees went, and I ſet them up both, but that which had moſt Bees, by little and little came to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; and I take the reaſon to be, for that both the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Bees were gone into the other hive, before I tooke it away, which the other could not finde, and therefore periſhed, as I ſay; for when I came to take a view of
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:159996:44"/>my Bees in Auguſt, I found that they had almoſt gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red nothing, which I doubted before, by their laſie go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out and in.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>It is a maruell that Mr. <hi>Southern</hi> ſhould be ſo much deceiued, to think there are no ſuch Bees, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the opinion of all men.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>As I ſaid before, ſo I ſay again, I do much wonder at it, in a man of any practice amongſt Bees, for by the very maſter Bees houſes, which he could not bee ignorant of, but muſt needs imagine ſuch a kinde of Bee. And I do verily beleeue that there is not any man that euer did driue a hive with any obſeruation, but will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn his opinion, as altogether abſurd, although that he neuer ſaw maſter Bee himſelfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>I pray ſhew unto me at large the difference you ſpeak of.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>You muſt underſtand, that all the other cels or holes, are made and placed in one uniform order, as a troop or ſquadron of ſouldiers ranged in order of bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, or lodged in a well pitched camp; euery cell or hole being ſix ſquare, according to the number of the Bees feet, and of the depth of a Bees length and ſomewhat more; and this order is double, as you ſee with a filme or ſtop in the midſt, that the one Bee cannot go thorow to another, ſo that the thickneſſe of this workmanſhip or frame, which we call a combe, is as thick as two Bees are long, and are commonly as broad as the hive is wide, and as long as the hive is deep: all which are placed ſo neere one to another, as the Bees may conueniently paſſe to and fro between the ſaid combes. But the maſter Bees houſes or cels are not ranged or placed in the forme and order of the reſt, but are ſeated upon ſome ſide or top or corner of a combe, in or neere ſuch places as the Bees
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:159996:45"/>moſt commonly paſſe by with their ſubſtance that they gather: and as the Captaines or other Commanders are pitcht in a camp, or in the head or place conuenient in a troop or ſquadron of ſouldiers. Againe, the faſhion of them is nothing like the other, but they are ſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly built round, thick and long, very artificiall and ſtately.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>Is there but one of them in a hive, or do they build many ſuch?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>There are ſundry of them in every hive, but the number is uncertaine, yet did I never ſee fewer then 5 or 6. nor ever aboue 9 or 10. which being placed and diſperſed into ſundry parts of the hive, ſeeme to be pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of remove as occaſion ſhall require, to overſee any part thereof.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>Doe not the Maſter Bees breed or ſpat in their houſes, as the other Bees doe in their Combes or Cells.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>Yes without all queſtion, for my ſelfe haue often times, found of their young in ſome of their hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of all ſorts, namely, ſome ready to flye, and ſome white ſpat, and they hold that theſe Bees have wings and feete at the firſt, and are not like a worme at all as the other Bees are.</p>
               <p>Theſe Maſter Bees are abſolute in their authorities and commands, and out of a regall power or civill diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline anſwerable to our Marſhall lawes, and as having a ſupreame prerogatiue aboue all the reſt, he over-view<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all that are within the compaſſe of his ſquadrons, he adminiſtreth Iuſtice unto all, correcting the lazie, floath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and diſobedient, and giving honour and incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to thoſe which are painefull, laborious and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent: In recompence whereof, and as it were a Tribute
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:159996:45"/>due unto him from their duties, they ofter unto him all their ſervices and loyalties, guarding and defending him from all dangers whatſoeuer, either civill and domeſtike, as in his owne hive, or forraine and abroad when they encounter with the aſſaults of other ſtrange Bees.</p>
               <p>This Maſter Bee doth not alone after a generall man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner take view of their generall labours, but particularly over-looketh every particular worke, every edifice, buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, ſtore-houſe, and whatſoever is neceſſary and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining either to the ſupport or maintenance of that little Commonwealth, and whereſoever he findeth er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, there he inforceth a preſent amendment.</p>
               <p>This Maſter Bee hath a ſting as well as the reſt, yet more for ornament then uſe, being ſo guarded and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended by thoſe Armies which incampe about him, that he ſeldome or never findeth any occaſion to imploy it?</p>
               <p>Againe, as he hath this generall guard of the whole multitude or Army of common ſouldiers, ſo he hath a ſellect and particular guard of choice officers or ſupreme Commanders, as Generalls, Lieutenant Generalls, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhalls, Sergeant-Majors, Colonells and Captains; and theſe whenſoeuer he pleaſeth to iſſue from his hive at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend on him in a ſingular and formall equipage, being ſo Marſhalled abroad and incamped at home, that no Millitary diſcipline can either exceed or amend the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of their orders; and thus much I think ſhall ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice concerning the breeding of Bees, and the power of the chiefe commander.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>Well Sir, now I pray you let me have your opinion concerning their order and manner of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſo much ſpoken of and admired, as well the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering themſelues in their hives, as in diſpoſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to labour abroad, and their gathering admirable
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:159996:46"/>and profitable commodities.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>They live together in their hives, as it were in a Campe, and duly keepe their watch and ward at the mouth or hole of their hive: in the morning you ſhall ſee them goe forth warily, not too far at the firſt, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if the weather be ſuſpitious, whereof they ſeeme to have ſome knowledge by a certaine kind of naturall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct, as the Poet hath well obſerved in theſe words.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vir.</hi> Nor from the hives if likely it be to raine,</l>
                  <l>They farre doe ſtray, nor truſt they will the skie,</l>
                  <l>If that the South winde blow but ſtill remaine</l>
                  <l>At home or buſied be with water nye.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Being loaded they flye with the wind: if any tempeſt ſuddenly ariſe, they countervaile themſelues with little ſtones, flying in the wind as neere the ground as may be, they labour both at home and aboard as appointed, as <hi>Virgil</hi> affirmeth in theſe words.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Some range for food,</l>
                  <l>And ply the fields abroad,</l>
                  <l>Some ſtill at home,</l>
                  <l>Doe labour buſily,</l>
                  <l>And round about with waxe,</l>
                  <l>The hives doe loade,</l>
                  <l>Which from the gummes,</l>
                  <l>They painefully doe trye.</l>
               </q>
               <p>For they gather the waxe of Flowers and gummy ſubſtances that they find, as may be well perceived by their going home loaden therewith, upon their legges and backs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Petralba.</speaker>
               <p>It is a common received opinion, that Bees gather as much honey of Flowers, as waxe, if not more.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tortona.</speaker>
               <p>I doe confeſſe it is, and I will not deny but that they may gather honey upon ſome Flowers, as up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:159996:46"/>the Bramble Flowers, Glover, and ſome other that bloſſome about the time of yeere when they gather moſt honey. Yet for the moſt part I am fully perſwaded they gather very little honey upon Flowers, but almoſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together waxe, except onely ſufficient to maintaine life, and to breed withall, and yet they want of that alſo in the dry and cold times that after happen in <hi>May</hi> &amp; <hi>Iune:</hi> but of this I haue ſpoken before; where I ſhewed what Trees and plants are good for Bees, and how the Bee garden ought to be acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modated with al things that are neceſſary for the benefit and increaſe, both of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and waxe. And ſo I conclude this ſhort diſcouſe or Hiſtory of Bees with that of <hi>Virgil,</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <q>Sic vos non vobis, &amp;c.</q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
